<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The renowned history, or the life and death of Guy Earl of Warwick Containing his noble exploits and victories.</title>
            <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831457</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60015)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2044:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The renowned history, or the life and death of Guy Earl of Warwick Containing his noble exploits and victories.</title>
                  <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Brugis for P. Brooksby at the Golden Ball near the Hospital-Gate in West-Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M D CLXXXI. [1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" is signed: John Shurly.</note>
                  <note>Most running titles read: Guy Earl of Warwick. The famous history of".</note>
                  <note>Final leaf contains advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  A-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: final page torn with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guy of Warwick (Legendary character) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:1"/>
            <p>The Renowned HISTORY, or the LIFE and DEATH of GUY EARL of WARWICK. CONTAINING His Noble EXPLOITS and VICTORIES.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of Guy on his horse</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Brugis</hi> for <hi>P. Brooksby</hi> at the <hi>Golden Hall</hi> near the <hi>Hoſpital-Gate</hi> in <hi>Weſt-Smithfield</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſile to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader I have here undertaken to give you a full and ſatisfactory Account of the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of the far-Famed and Moſt Renowned <hi>Engliſh</hi> Champion <hi>GUY</hi> Earl of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> according to what can be Collected out of the beſt Hiſtorians, both Antient and Modern. No Work in this Nature ever yet appearing to the World with more then half a Face, or an imperfect Relation, the which has rather ſullied the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Actions of ſo brave a man, then cauſed them to ſhine in their Native Brightneſs, which was one of the chief Cauſes that incited me to venture this vaſt Scene, which includes not only <hi>Europe,</hi> but great part of <hi>Aſia</hi> e'r it can be finiſhed, having ever had a Veneration for the Memories of Worthy men I thought not fit to let ſuch Lawrels wither in the duſt as hertofore have flouriſhed on the Brows of our Renowned Hero, <hi>England's</hi> greateſt boaſt, well knowing how great an Ingratitude it is, to let that Honour lye buryed in ſilence that of the Nation has deſerved ſo well: and above all, I conſider there is no greater Spur to prick forwards the minds of men to undertake Great Deſigns and Vallarous Exploits, than by Reading the worthy Deeds of ſuch as have thereby attained to the height of Glory: For ſtories of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and of Warlike Enterprizes, if drawn to the Life, do moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as it were) bear fire in themſelves, the which often ſo inflames the Souls of youth, that it ſtirs them up with a deſire to imitate the ſame, and the very remembrance inſpires them with courage, for the Soul of man being compoſed of a fiery ſubſtance, if not reſtrained by dulneſs and groſs Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the body, will be ever reaching after this ſubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, placed in a more then ordinary Sphear, eſpecially in <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> who at this day are Famed for Courage and true Heroick Vallor through all the yet known World. No Nation under Heaven but in that muſt give us the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencey, or we may juſtly claim it as our Birthrights. And now dear Countrey-men ſince I have taken ſome ſmall pains in drawing out this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory as near as poſſible to the Life, I hope you will be ſo juſt to the Memory of this Renowned Earl, as to read over his Warlike and Pious Actions, if not to imitate them, which is the only wiſh of him who is a greater admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of true worth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Country man to ſerve you <hi>JOHN SHURLY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:4"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>HOw <hi>Guy</hi> Lineally deſcended from <hi>Caſſibilanus,</hi> the Pamous Britiſh Prince, with a brief Account of the Roman and Saxon Conqueſt over this Iſle of <hi>Guy's</hi> Birth and Parentage, his Youthful Exploits and firſt falling in Love with <hi>Phaelice,</hi> and what paſſed between them, how ſhe ſent him abroad to Fight, having been admoniſhed of his warlike Exploits in a Dream, how <hi>Guy</hi> Landing in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> killed two Champions and grievouſly wounded the third, freeing a Lady who was wrongfully condemned to dye, how he was purſued by Duke <hi>Philbertus,</hi> how he fought with him at Sea and took him Priſoner, how he worſted all the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Princes, and won from them the Emperours Daughter, he returning here to <hi>England</hi> kills the monſtrous Dun Cow, after being ſent abroad he kills ſixteen of Duke <hi>Ottons</hi> men who lay in a wood to intercept his Life; aſſiſts the Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain</hi> againſt <hi>Lorain,</hi> raiſes the Siege with a dreadful overthrow, afterwards makes Peace, and with two thouſand men puts to Sea in order to the Relief of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantium,</hi> Beſieged by the Turks, meets with ſeveral Pirates and deſtroyes many of them, raiſes the Siege and kills ſeveral of the Pagan Champions, routing their Armies: <hi>Terty</hi> wounded and his Lady taken from him, the which he reſtores and aſſists his Father, Beſieged by Duke <hi>Otton</hi> whom he in ſingle Combate kild, a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon and a Bore, then returns to <hi>England</hi> and kills another Dragon in <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> after that, is Married, then departs on <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> to the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> Kills <hi>Amarant</hi> a huge Giant and delivers thoſe that he kept in Tortures, routs <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manthus</hi> and reſtores Earl <hi>Terry</hi> to his Earldome, returns to <hi>England</hi> Combats <hi>Colbron</hi> the Daniſh Giant and kills him, put the Armies to rout, freeing <hi>England,</hi> then lives in a Cave unknown to all bus the King, at his death ſeads <hi>Phaelice</hi> his Ring, who coming to him cloſed his Eyes, and ſhortly after dyes her ſelf for grief, are ſplendidly buryed in one Tombe, with an Epitaph infixed, and many other particulars more at large.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">A Brief Narration of the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Saxon</hi> Conqueſt made of this Iſland, and of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it endured, which brings us to the Birth and Lineal decent of our Famous Champion the Heroick Earl.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen Rome had ſpread her Enſignes wide into the world, and made moſt Nations yield unto her Arms, <hi>France</hi> totally ſubdued ſome wenty years before our Saviours Birth: <hi>Caeſar</hi> ambitious of more Honour, from the diſtant ſhore, caſt his Eyes on this our Brittiſh Iſle, encloſed with white Rocks, (from whence moſt do affirm it took its name) and rounded with the Sea, then wild and barbarous, without Law or civil Cuſtomes; all painted people and in manners ſtrange) yet the great Warriour fired with ſucceſsful Fortune, regarding not the People but the Land, deſirous to anex it to his Conqueſts, and the Roman Empire, by reaſon of its temperate and pleaſant ſcituation; ſet ſail from <hi>Callis</hi> with <hi>200</hi> Ships, thinking with his experienced Legions and old Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers trained in War, in a ſhort ſpace to over run this Iſle, then ignorant in ſeats of Arms; but ere he Landed, found true Brittiſh valour ſo beyond his expectation, that he ſtood amazed: for the Britains having notice of the Invaſion, all aſſembled under their ſeveral Kings or Princes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſibilain</hi> a Famous Britain, then being chief; from whom renowned <hi>Guy</hi> our famous Engliſh Champion ſprung; they encountered the Romans ſo fiertely at their Landing, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf was forced ſhamefully to retreat with the lsſs of his own ſword, and ſeveral Enſigns and Standards were taken, his Army broken and he forced back to <hi>France</hi> to make Recruits: ſuch was the valour then our Nation bore, and at the firſt onſet foiled proud <hi>Rome,</hi> to whoſe dread Arms the world thier portion homage paid, nor did ſhe make a Conqueſt here at laſt by the Sword, but after infinite loſs and twenty years toil, was forced to grant the Britains their own terms; the which was in the Reign of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> about the time of our Saviours birth, that Prince of peace who eſtabliſhed peace through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world; and for <hi>400</hi> years that the Roman Emperours by their Lieutenants Ruled this Iſle, no nation afforded more valiant &amp; redoubted men, who were continually drawn out for to ſupply their Armies in moſt quarters of the world: till the Red horſe went out to take peace from the Earth, and the Roman Empier was grown ſo great, that the bole was not able to ſupport the branches; whereupon the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> breaking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italy,</hi> tore it in pieces ſo that the Romans to ſave their own nearer home abandoned this Iſle, and carried with them all the flower of Bririſh Chivalry; upon which the Scots and Picts taking the advantage, overrun the Northern parts, deſtroying all with ſire &amp; ſword <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lamentably, that the diſtreſſed Britains were forced to call unto their aid the Saxons, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arlik people that then flouriſhed in <hi>Germany</hi> which helped but to make their miſeries the
<pb facs="tcp:35920:5"/>greater, for after they had ſubdued the Britiſh Enemies, they became worſe Enemies themſelves; for <hi>Hingeſt</hi> and <hi>Horſus</hi> their two Captains, obſerving the fruitfulneſs and pleaſant Cituation of the Countrey, were loath to return to their own barren ſoyl without good Bootyes; whereupon, and the better to create a quarrel, the former Married his Daughter to <hi>Vortimor</hi> the Britiſh King (deſcended lineally from the before mentioned <hi>Caſſibilain</hi>) raiſed no ſmall regret amongſt the Britiſh Nobility, eſpecially becauſe through her means the Saxons were preferred to the chief Dignities, the which increaſed their intereſt, &amp; got them ſirmer footing in the Land, of which they complaining to the King and finding no Redreſs, put ſome Affronts upon the Saxon Chiefs, who glad of any opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for to beget a quarrel thereupon (as they pretended for want of their promiſed pay) ſeized ſeveral Towns wherein their Soldiers were quartered; this Allarmd the Britains, who Headed by the young Prince <hi>Vortimors</hi> Son, overthrew them in a pitched Battel though not without muth ſlaughter on both ſides: and after having driven them out of all their places of ſtrength, obliged them to leave the Land; but long they reſted not content, for the next year having gathered a great ſtrength, they ſet ſail for this Iſle, the ſhores of which were ſo manfully defended againſt them, that they finding no poſſibility to Land, deſired a Truce, and that they might Treat with the Britiſh Nobility about delivering them their Daughter; the which after ſome debate was granted, and about ſixty of the Saxons came on ſhore privately Armed to Treat with the like number of Britains; and in the midſt of the Treaty, every Saxon (as it was before contrived amongſt them) ſlew his man, unleſs one who Treated with (as ſome ſay) the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> the Earl ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Treathery prevented him by pulling up a hedgeſtake, with which he heat out his brains, and ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d five or ſix more, himſelf getting away with only a ſlight wound in the leſt arm. The chief Nobility being thus murthered by Treathery, the amazed Britains Retreated, and gave the Saxons opportunity to Land, the which they had no ſooner done, but they fell to their old trade of laying all waſt with fire and ſword; the which they exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ented with ſuch cruelty, as made the people fly before them to the Mountains (which are now talled <hi>Wales,</hi> and are the real antient Britains) leaving their houſes and what they could not carry or drive away to the ravage of the bloody Conquerors, who devided the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into ſeven parts, and named it a Hepterchy, each portion having a King over it, which continued ſo in civil wars amongſt themſelves about three hundred years, till it was totally ſubdued by <hi>Edgard</hi> the great King of the Weſt-Saxons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>named <hi>Athelſtone</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſixt year of whoſe Reign was the ever famous Champion <hi>Giraldus Caſſibilanius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> called <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who as credible Hiſtorians do affirm, deſcended lineally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om the Britiſh Royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ood, ever ſince <hi>Caſſibilanius</hi> the warlike Prince before recited, through the many changes and miſeries of War clouded in obſcurity, which no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be the Subject of this enſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Hiſtory; ſince we have already ſhown you the miſerie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of truel War, and the bravery of Britiſh ſpirits under ſuch afflictions, and traced through
<pb facs="tcp:35920:5"/>the many adverſe windings the deſcent of our Hero, <hi>Englands</hi> chief glory, whoſe name will live while time ſhall be no more.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>And ſtill be ſounded by the trump of Fame,</l>
                  <l>Where e'r ſhe Engliſh Valour does proclaim.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> deſcended from <hi>Caſſibilanius</hi> the Renowned Britiſh Prince, of his Birth and Youthful Exploits: and how he fell in Love with <hi>Phaelice</hi> the Earls beauteous Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and how ſhe deſpiſed his ſuit.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>GUy rald us Caſſibilanius</hi> Son of <hi>Gordian Caſlibilanius</hi> (but more vulgarly known by the name of <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwick,</hi> by which name we muſt trace the Hiſtory of his Life) born in the famous City of <hi>Warwick,</hi> in the Sixth year of the Reign
<pb facs="tcp:35920:6"/>of <hi>Edgard</hi> the Great, his Father being an accompliſhed Gentleman, and had formerly a very good Estate in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> which he was forced to part with, to ſave his life, at the time of his being taken Priſoner; for bearing Arms under the ſubdued Saxon King of <hi>Mercia:</hi> Vpon which reſignation obtaining his Liberty from the Martial in whoſe cuſtody he was, he came to <hi>Warwick</hi> and there ſo well behaved himſelf that he won the affections and good likeing of all the Gentry, but eſpecially of Earl <hi>Robands,</hi> whom the King had made Governour of the Town and Caſtle; who took him into his houſe and made him his Steward; in which place he behaved himſelf ſo well, that he won the affections of a Kinghts Daughter in the Town, which he married, and on her begat renowned <hi>Guy,</hi> the ſubject of this famous Hiſtory, who might be ſaid like <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> from his very infancy to be made for War, and great Exploits; being ſo well limb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from head to foot, as might denote a ſtout and Warlike Hero would in time from that bold infant riſe; nay, and his mothers Dreams preſaged no leſs: for during her preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, ſhe fancied that <hi>Mars</hi> deſcended in a bloody Chariot drawn by two fiery Dragons, and told her, that the infant that her womb contained, ſhould be the Glory of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo great in Arms renownd, as ſhould amaze mankind and he the terrour of the Pagan world; this ſhe declared to the Counteſs of <hi>VVarwick</hi> about a moneth before her delivery, which after wards proved true, as ſhall amply he related: For no ſooner had he attained to eight years of age, but he began to practice skill in Wraſtling, Running, Throwing ſtones, and other Exertiſes that his tender years were capable of, in which he exceeded all that were much older and far bigger than himſelf, to the admiration of of thoſe that obſerved him more curiouſly; his delight was in hardſhips and laborious exerciſe, and ſo continued till ſixteen, at which age few men could encounter with him, be then was uſed to enter the Liſt, and whereſoever he came, alwaies came off with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. Inſomuch that the Earl hearing of his unmatched exploits, ſent for him and entertained him at dinner with himſelf and ſeveral of the Gentry of that Countrey, but above all <hi>Phaelice</hi> his beauteous daughter, Angel bright, and with accompliſhed Graces Fraught, on whom <hi>Guy</hi> firing his youthful eyes, immediately felt Loves Arrows wound his ſoul, and paſſion, like a Fever burned within; ſtill as he gazed he felt new flames, and ſo unexpected a ſurpriſe, that all began to wonder at the ſuddain change; his Father demanded the cauſe, but could not get the ſecret from his breſt, it ſtuck too cloſe, yet after the ſumptuous repaſt he played ſeveral Prizes before the Earl, and being ſtung by Love, grew more fierce againſt his Cumbatants; or perhaps to ſhew the Lady his Valour, and to make her to have ſome eſteem of his worth; ſo that at Wraſtling, Back-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>word, Faulcheon, or the like, none were able to ſtand before him; for his force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>med more than man, and all that he ſtruck or laid his hand upon he felled or tumbled to the ground; ſo that at the laſt none durſt Encounter him: he ſeeing that, put on his Clothes, and going to the Earl humbly deſired his Licence to retire himſelf, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>for refreſhment; at which the Earl embracing him, ſaid, <hi>Go thou worthy Youth our Nations Pride,</hi> and withal gave him a Ring ſet with Diamonds, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſeveral other Noble men made him Preſants, the which he unwillingly received, modeſtly excuſing the Applauſes, and Favours they had heaped upon him, ſaying, <hi>he was not worthy of them, and that his whole Lives Service muſt make them Reſtitution for thoſe benefits he had received at their hands,</hi> which modeſtly made them yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him more, and have a greater Eſteem of his Vertues, and each was the more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of his company; but at his earneſt requeſt, and the approach of night they diſmiſſed him, upon his promiſe to attend them the next day; after he was departed, and the Table ſumptuouſly ſpread, wine in abundance was called for, and ſupper no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but the Earl began <hi>Guys</hi> health, each of the Lords and Gentry preſant pledging it with their hats <hi>off.</hi> Such Fame got he by his prevailing manhood, after which round their whole diſcourſe was of his hopefulneſs, and the great Endowments that Nature and Art had conſpired to beſtow upon, <hi>Guys</hi> Father was muth joyed in his happy Son, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But now we muſt leave them in the midſt of their Iollitry, and ſollow <hi>Guy</hi> into his ſecret retirement, where being arrived, he began to contemplate upon what he had ſeen, and could hardly perſwade himſelf that ſhe was mortal, ſo far his fancy wrought upon her perfections, for indeed ſhe was fair even to a Miracle, ſo that that age afforded her no parallel; for Eyes ſhe had that gliſtered like two Stars, ſhaded with eyehrows plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold, a fair high Forehead, and cheeks as ſmooth as Alablafter, in which the Roſes and the Liſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies mired ſo pure, that none could diſcern which had the ſuperiority, her Teeth like orient Pearls, encloſed with Coral Lips, and ſuch a winning ſmile as might raviſh the beholder, with a ſmooth chin tranſparent, whilſt in curious wreaths her Golden Treſſes hung; to theſe add a majestick grace and comly mean: To ſumme up all Natures maſterpiece, the only wonder of her ſex. Theſe conſidered, wrackt poor <hi>Guy</hi> almoſt to deſpair of ever attaining ſuch an accompliſhed creature, while thus he gives his paſſion vent, how am I loſt, for ever loſt, in what a pathleſs maze is it I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, can Loves ſoves force be ſuch, to wound a heart that never injured his deity; but if it muſt be ſo, that it is thy ſport (winged god) to wound us Mortals with thy ſtaming ſhafts let her (in whoſe bright eyes thou ſateſt when firſt thou wingedſt them with her Glances and darted them into my breaſt) feell an equal paſſion, or elſe tis Tyranny to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orture one thou art not purpoſed to relieve: how am I wrapped in clouds, not knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here I am, ſo quickly ſnarched into the unknown Regions, where I cannor turn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the right or to the left, but muſt either ſore aloft, or fall into confuſion, wild and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the latter is ſure if nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>revented by the ſouner; for me to attain that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>auteous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly form divine, my ſoul-deſire, I fear is altogether impoſſible, by reaſon of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e diſſance in our Fortunes, ſhe to high and I ſo mean and low; yet that me thinks
<pb facs="tcp:35920:7"/>ſhould not divide us; Love is far more pure than Gold, and wieneſs my wounds its forte is irreſiſtable: O ye powers! for what are theſe treated beings, theſe ſoſter heau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties if not to be enjoyed? or did ye ſend theſe Angellick ſhapes from your bright abodes, only to be gazed upon and wondered at by Love-ſick man, and puniſh him by what he never muſt poſſeſs; tis ſure they were not, nor can ſuch lovely ſhapes lodge curelty, or proud disdain within their breaſts, why then neglect I to declare my ſuit? who knows but ſhe may prove kind or burn with equal flame? ſeeing her eyes bent equally with mine, and glance for glance ſhe often ſent, and now and then a heavenly ſmile which ended in a bluſh; I'l be no longer tortured thus between hope and deſpair, but will go to her, and with low obedience tell her <hi>that I Love,</hi> ſo receive my ſentance of Life or Death from her fair lips; but alaſs! how ſhall I do it, ſeeing I am unskilful in that grand affair? aſſiſt me then thou god of Love, and ſend one of thy golden ſhafts before to make me room &amp; yeild me ſuccesful in this my bold attempt, Virgin I come, my Fever burns wo fierce to be delayed.</p>
               <p>So ſaying, he ſtayed his language with a peal of ſighs, ſtrait aroſe from the ſolitary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bed whereon he lay, &amp; in the beſt attice he had, poſted to <hi>Warwick Caſtle</hi> where he heard his Love was gone to recreate her ſelf, but ſcartely was he entered, ere he met the Earl with many of the Gentry, preparing for a Hunting match, all of them welcoming <hi>Guy,</hi> and deſired his company, but he excuſed himſelf by telling them he was much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſpoſed, and ſo with much adoe obtained his exemption of the Earl, who immediately ſent for his Phyſitian, and gave him ſtrickt charge to be careful of his bealth and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: ſo the Earl to Hunting rode, and <hi>Guy</hi> was conducted to his Chamber, where the Phyſitian made no ſmall ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to enquire into the Nature of his Malady; but the more he ſought the more be found himſelf at a loſs; at which he perceiving <hi>Guy</hi> to ſmile diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deinfully, the better to ſave his credit, told him he muſt be dieted, blooded, and keep his chamber, or his diſtemper would grow worſe; to which, <hi>Guy</hi> riſing from his ſeat, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; Truly Father, at this time of your preſcriptions, ther's no need, nor can your Art afford the leaſt rellef, no <hi>Gallen</hi> or <hi>Hipocrates</hi> themſelves were they alive and both here preſent, could not give me eaſe; tis my ſelf muſt be my own Phyſitian, or my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady muſt reign for ever over me: There is a ſlower as I have lately heard, of precious worth, growing in this Caſtle, the which could I once pluck, would eaſe me in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; at which the Doctor ſtood in admiration, wondring what ſtower he meant, why truly ſir ſaid he tis called <hi>Happy,</hi> indeed quath the Doctor happineſs is good, but as for a flower of that name, in all my curious ſearch I never found nor heard of, pray ſir ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> leave me, and I ſear not but to find it out, for I am ſure it grows within the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> walls; at which the Doctor took his leave, and <hi>Guy</hi> aſcended up the Caſtle ſtairs to vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the proſpect of the Gardens round, into which he had no ſooner caſt his eyes but he beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the beauteous maid that was ſole Empreſs of his heart, ſitting alone in a ſhady Bov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35920:7"/>to ſcreen her from the ſuns hot Rays, while before her the ſpringing water of a Criſtal Fountain played and ſent refreſhment to each fragrant flower or lovely plant that crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the happy place, reſembling another Paradiſe, and ſhe the firſt created woman; theſe <hi>Guy</hi> takes as happy Omens and reſolves to venture now for life or death, and thus invokes Loves Deity to aid him in the great deſign. Oh propitious power, if ever, now prove kind in aiding thy humble ſuppliant, who is all obedience unto thy commands and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies his unſpotted vows at thy great Altar, which ever blazes bright with ſlaming hearts of Lovers, offered up as Trophies of thy power; aſſiſt me to Court this famous beauty, and teach me how to wooe and how to Conquer her who has already conquored me: ſo ſaying, he deſcended with all ſpeed, and coming to the Garden gate, knocked ſoftly, and ſoon found admittance by one of the Damſels that waited on fair <hi>Phaelice,</hi> the which he no ſooner had, but compoſing his warlike face into the beſt form he could; he made towards her with low reverence, who (expecting he came with ſome meſſage from her Father) roſe up to meet him, when <hi>Guy</hi> with Love ſurtharged, thus began.</p>
               <p>Faireſt of Creatures, brighteſt of your ſexes, made of ſuch kindred mould to Heaven that you ſeem Angelical, a goddeſs all divine; therefore I have here brought a heart by Loves command to offer at your ſhrine; O frown not on me with disdainful Eyes, leaſt with ſuch a look death enter and deſtroy the man that ever ſhall admire, and with this awful diſtance adore your matchleſs Virtues; deſpiſe me not thou only center of my ſoul, who loves thee more than life, O that I could expreſs my boundleſs paſſion, or that thou couldſt look into my breaſt, and there behold how the tormenting flames ſtill roal about my heart, that with a continual Fever burns, in which the Arrows of your pointed beauty ſtick; that Lords and Noble men have courted you I am not ignorant, but none could Love like me; pardon my boldneſs Lady, that to ſave my life I ſue, with the ſame fear a guilty priſoner beholds his angry Judge; for your power's for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when Life or death depends upon your ſmiles or frowns.</p>
               <p>To whom thus <hi>Phaelice</hi> with majeſtick countenance replyed: Alas ſir, Love is ſuch a thildiſh toy I ne'r intend to try it, thereſore ceaſe your vain ſuit, a Virgins happy life ſhall be my choice for ever; Love is but a dream compoſed of idle ſanties, and that I ſhould wound you is impoſſible, or if ſuch it could be, you them muſt blame your raſh and unadviſed folly, to attempt things ſo far above your reath; could you imagine that the Heir of <hi>Warwick</hi> would ere condeſcend to Marry with one ſo far beneath in birth, and in each dagree unſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, no therefore I would adviſe you to deſiſt this enterprize, leaſt it come unto my Fathers rat, and beget the ſharp rebuke.</p>
               <p>So ſaying ſhe ended, and <hi>Guy</hi> prepared to anſwer, hut ſhe turned away disdainfully and left hun to himſelf now hopeleſs, perplered and tortured worſe than ever.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Curſing the cruel Stars that ruled his birth</l>
                  <l>And wiſhing now to be no more on Earth</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> being denyed, fell diſtracted for a time, till <hi>Cupid</hi> repreſenting him in a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like poſture, and declaring what wonders ſhould be wrought by him to <hi>Phaelice</hi> in her ſleep, telling her it was his mothers command that ſhe ſhould love him, whereupon ſhe granted her conſent upon condition of his performing glorious enterprizes.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>HAlf diſtracted with what had paſſed, <hi>Guy</hi> retires to his Fathers houſe thinking to ſhake off the Chains of Love, or burſt them by ſome other means; for like <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les's</hi> yovſon'd ſhirt, the more he ſtrove the more the venom worked and the diſtentper fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him whereſoever he went, for which he finding no relief, grew frantick for a time, quite bereft of ſence or reaſon, and to this purpoſe uttered his phrenſies and ran into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order far beyond <hi>Orlando</hi> or <hi>Oreſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:8"/>
               <p>Am I then ſlighted <hi>(ſald he)</hi> who evermore will truſt to woman-kind? accurſed cruel Love, couldſt thou leave me thus? can ſhe not Love, or loves ſhe ſome one elſe, which hinders her Love from paſſing unto me? O that I knew my Rival, my dread arm ſhould hurl ſuch vengean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> an his hend as ſhould amaze mankind; I'd drag him cound the world, ore Sea and Land, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him into circling fires, plung him into roaring <hi>Erebus,</hi> there to broyl in Brimſtone flames and ſcorched for ever. O <hi>Jove Jove!</hi> Ile to thy Courts and hollow loud, nay I will thunder to your regardleſs power, and make you deaf with everlaſting cries, from the Suns bright Chariot ſnatch <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cherial</hi> ſire, ſet your Celeſtial manſions in a blaze, melt down your golden Roofs, and make your gates of Adamant fly from off their Tiamond hinges; arm my ſelf with Lightning, and make vollued thunders roar around the world; <hi>Eacus, Mines, Rodomanthus,</hi> and all the black Infernal powers, what have ye done, my Love ſhe's loſt, for ever gone; ſink ſink earths frame to thy firſt Chaos, and with thy ruine cruſh mankind; drop, drop ye ctars and ever wakeful Tapers of the Skies, and let combuſtive flames purge this groſſer world; O ſhe's gone, the Beauties gone, now night and darkneſs ceaſe me, and eternal ſlumbers ſeal my Eyes.</p>
               <p>Thus ſaying, he groand and ſmote his breſt, pull'd off his hair, and in diſiracted ſort continued till <hi>Phaelice</hi> being admoniſhed by <hi>Cupid</hi> in a dream, ſent him more comſortable hopes of her enſuing favours.</p>
               <p>When Night had drawn her Curtain, and the world in ſilence ſate, each mortal in ſweet ſlumbers was repoſed, <hi>Morbheus</hi> the Leaden god of ſleep from his drowſy Coves, by <hi>Venus</hi> command, couſed up his Viſionary forms, the which in various ſhapes preſent themſelves to men, and one of the Faries dreſſed in <hi>Cupid's</hi> wonted guiſe, with Bow and Quiver, armed, preſents it to the fancy of the ſlumbering <hi>Phaelice,</hi> to whom the ſhade being inſtructed, thus began.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phaelice,</hi> behold I from the Queen of Love my beauteous Mother, come to preſent unto thee this Martial Here, and with that a ſhade all clad in Aemour appeared repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Guy</hi> ſo to the life, that ſhe knew him at firſt, and ſtarted in her ſleep, while thus the wing'd form proceeded: This is the man deſigned for thee, whoſe warlike deads ſhall make the world amazed; and to ſuch Fame ſhall ſoon ariſe that Kings and Princes ſhall be proud to court him, whilſt the terrour of his arm ſhall ſpread over greateſt part of the Earth; a friend to the diſtreſſed, and the oppreſſors foe; Fortune ſhall wait on him, and Conquering Laurels ſtill be green upon his brows; deſpiſe him not fair Virgin for his want of wealth, it is the treaſure of the mind that makes a man truly great; for know, Beauty was at firſt treated free, e'r Gold was known or from the vowels of the Earth was brought to light, and ſince it has been in eſtimation, it has corrupied innocence, and Vertue ſpoiled, therefore is to be deſpiſed in caſe of Love, that intellectual Eſſence and bright jewel of the Soul; then as the powers above decree take him, for his manhood and
<pb facs="tcp:35920:9"/>accompliſhed virtues think him worthy of your Love even at the higheſt rate, for it is moſt aſſured he is ſo.</p>
               <p>So ſaid the Form, and <hi>Cupid</hi> that was not wanting in the enterpriſe drew up his Bow charged with a Golden ſhaft and aimed directly at <hi>Phaelice</hi> heart, the which no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er done, but ſwift as Lightning ſlew the ſinging Arrow through the yielding air, and fixed its point direct, at which the ſtartling Virgin waked, and wondred to find a fire ſo quickly kindled in her breaſt, ſo that contemplating on the Viſion, ſhe thus began to ſigh her paſſion out.</p>
               <p>Alas and art thou gone thou winged power, what thange is this I feel, I that ſo late deſpiſed all Love, and laughed at Lovers pains, now feell a fever in my breſt that wiſt conſume me if it get not vent; can it be <hi>Guy</hi> that I muſt Love my Fathers Stewards Son that I denyed, muſt I now ſue to him, perhaps now he will deſpiſe me for negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting him, and triumph over my weakneſs: O <hi>Cupid</hi> are thy Laws then ſo ſevere? pardon my offence and ſle hereafter grow more mild, and pitty Lovers in diſtreſs.</p>
               <p>While ſhe was thus ſtruggling with her flame <hi>Guy,</hi> having recovered his ſenſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to Retreat like a Coward, but Rally once more and try his Fortune, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome ſearch, having found her in her Chamber he thus begins.</p>
               <p>Moſt Beauteous, though ſevere, to you once more I have preſumed to come, not as a Suitor now, but as a condemned Priſoner, deſiring you to ſtrike the fatal ſtroak, that can only ſet my ſoul at reſt, for I have born my torture long enough; no Tirant Love I can endure no more; therefore ſweet Lady in pitty to a wounded Lover, if any pitty lodges in that fair breaſt, ſtrike deeper, yer at laſt, prove kind and eaſe my pain, ſo ſaying he ſighed and tears burſt from his warlike Eyes, not knowing that the powerful god of Love had mollified her heart and made her ſenſible of his command &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The which <hi>Phaelice</hi> obſerving, began to bluſh, whilſt in her fair cheeks the Roſes Conqueſt over the Lillies gained; then fetching an undiſcovered ſigh began no followech. Alas you ask what is not mine to grant; know gentle youth I at my Father's diſpoſal a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, nor without him dare I conſent to ought, for ſhould I how prove diſobedient, who ſo long have been obedient to his juſt Commands; what would the world of <hi>Phaelice</hi> ſay? each tongue would wound my Faine ſo deep that naught but death could yield relief; nor ſhould I ſo eſcape, for in the ſilent grave they would aſperſe me, and fix Reproach upon my Comb: To which, thus anſwered <hi>Guy,</hi> Fair Lady, doubt not your Fathers free con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiſt, for with this arm I will ſo far purchaſe the good eſteem of the Renowned Earl, that my marchleſs deeds, inſtend of Gold ſhall win his greatneſs to accept of me your humble ſlave for his obedient Son, ſo ended he, and ſhe inflamed with Love, yet willing to hide it for a time, began; Go then and in fierce Arms your Fame advance, court breadful Battels while <hi>Victoria</hi> Crowins your head with her Triumphant Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and when laven with the ſpoils of War, or great Archievements, you returne
<pb facs="tcp:35920:9"/>that I may ſafely yield without a ſtain to Honour, I ſhall be all your own, till then I ſhall remain in Virgin-ſtate your conſtant <hi>Phaelice</hi> ever.</p>
               <p>At which <hi>Guy</hi> overjoyed, with humble thanks vowed low as Earth, and at laſt through the greeſs, his Language found a paſſage, while theſe words he uttered: bright Star, by whoſe divine influence my ſoul is guided and diſpoſed; If feats of Arms, greatneſs in Battel gained, will pleaſe my Love, through ſeas of blood ile wade, climb to the higheſt Turret in Fames brazen Tower, and from thence look down upon the Coward world, with Gh for <hi>Caeſar</hi> now, or the dread Conquerour of the Eaſt, I ſeell new force, and on a ſuddain am grown more then man, i'm all on fire till my great task's begun, and for a time I willingly forego thy beauteous face, which ne'rtheleſs ſhall be for ever ſtamped upon my ſoul; my Love farwel, to Arms I muſt repair, for this ſweet Kiss that I imprint upon thy Corral lips, ile write thy name in Crimſon Characters upon the breaſts of Earths proud Champions, that when they ſee them they may think of thee.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Again Farwel my Love, I muſt away</l>
                  <l>To find the coaſt where Glory bates to day.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> putting to Sea landed in <hi>Normandy,</hi> where be fought with three Champions, killing two of them, and wounded the third, raking from them a Lady wrongfully condemned to dy by the young Duke of <hi>Bilois</hi> who had Raviſht her, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>NOw <hi>Guy</hi> having taken his leave of <hi>Phaelice,</hi> prepares for <hi>France,</hi> &amp; Embarquinng ſet Sail, with pronuſe of quick art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al there, but no ſooner was the Ship ſome
<pb facs="tcp:35920:10"/>ren Leagues off from ſhoar but the Winds began to blow hard from the South Weſt, and black Clouds overſpread the face of Heaven, and laud thunders from the Northern round began to roar, ſo that in ſhort time a dreadful ſtorm aroſe, while ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning darted thick, and made the Sea ſeem all on ſire, the Waves incaged by the winds mounted high, and ſeem to mix with pitchy clouds, and bandied the Ship from ſide to ſide, ſo that they rode on furiouſly before the Guſts all that day and all the following night, not having ſo much as the proſpect of Sun, Moon or Star, but early the next morning, the Marriners from the Top-maſt-head deſcryed Land, to which, the winds being ſomewhat abated, they made; and about ten in the morning ſound it to be <hi>Harflew</hi> in <hi>Normandy</hi> where they put in ſafe, after an hours continuance in the Port, <hi>Guy</hi> and the Captain of the Veſſel went a ſhore to refreſh themſelves, where they had not long been, e'r they heard loud ſhouts, and the noiſe of Drums and Trumpets, the which was moſt acceptable to <hi>Guy,</hi> for now he thought there was ſome work for him in hand, whereupon he called his Hoſt, and demanded the cauſe, who with countenance ſad, which ſhewed a ſenſe of grief, toſd him that a beauerous young Lady of that place, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> by name, having been ſately Raviſhed by one of the Duke <hi>de Biloys's</hi> Sons, the which black crime, four Ruſſins were ſubborned to ſwear that the fact was done by ſome other perſon, and that ſhe had confeſſed ſhe only laid it upon the young Lord to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Marriage, in revenge for breaking his promiſe that ſhe pretended he had made to her; upon which the old Duke grew ſo incenſed, by reaſon his ſon was in a ſhort time to be Married to the Printeſs of <hi>Parma;</hi> that he condemned her to he Burnt, unleſs any Champion would he ſo kind as to vindicate her innocence by fighting with her ſour Accuſers one after another; this News was welcome unto <hi>Guy,</hi> as hoping now to try his firſt Erperiment, ſo that turning from his Hoſt to the Captain, he ſold, Sir, I think this enterprize is worthy of an Engliſh ſword, and that wronged Benuty ought not to be left thus, in diſtreſs; perhaps the Dukes power over-aws thoſe that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to venture their lives in her behalf, and ſo the innocent muſt periſh, whilſt the Guilty ſhall go free: what ſay you Captain, ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> if I adventure to preſerve her, truly ſaid the Captian I think it a meritorious Exploit, could you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bieve it with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, but I hold it no wisdome to hazard your life for the ſake of a ſtranger whom you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw; truly ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> I leſt my Native Soyl for that intent, my buſineſs is only to win Fame at the hazard of my Life my Fortune, to help the weak againſt the mighty, and to relieve thoſe that appreſſing Tyrants cruſh: ſo ſaying, he gave order for his Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe and Arms ſtrait to be brought on ſhore, ſo accoutring himſelf in his Warlike Habille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he took leave of his Hoſt and the Captain, who endeavoured all they could to perſwade him from the Enterprize, but in vain; for having deſired the Captain who
<pb facs="tcp:35920:11"/>would willingly have accompanied him to await his return, he ſet ſpurs to his Horſe and Riding to the place where his Hoſt had directed him, he found a great concourſe of people ſtanding round in a Ring made by the Marſhal ſo appointed, in the middle of which was faſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned to a Stake the fair <hi>Derinda,</hi> and by her ſtood her weeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, on whom <hi>Guy</hi> fixing his eyes was moved to pitry, and more eager to vindicate her with his Arms, the which he had ſcarce time to think upon, before the Ruſſins (who had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the Lady) entered the Liſt, well mounted and well Armed, proudly wheeling to the Right and Left, and then making a ſtand, one of them with a loud voice, dentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded who among the Aſſembly there preſent it was that durſt, in behalf of that baſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (pointing to the diſconſolate Lady) enter the Liſt, for ſayes he, although the Dukes pleaſure is that he ſhall Combate with us four, yet I alone ſtand ready to receive him on my Launces point, and in death make him repent the undertaking of a Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets cauſe, while theſe my companions have no work left to do: This made <hi>Guy</hi> ſtorm, ſo that his countenance to terrour changed, whereupon he bid make way, and with an undaunted courage entring, thus ſpake: See here preſumtious man, a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion that dares vindicate this Lavies cauſe, and prove her innocent, not ſingly with one will I diſpute, but with you all at once to have the ſooner done; this ſo inraged the Frenchman that inſtantly he bid the ſignal Trumpet ſound, at which both couched their Spears, and as ſwift as Lightning in the midway meet, whilſt the horſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dring hoofs made earth beneath them tremble, <hi>Guy's</hi> Spear came plum upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and through his Armour, and his ſhirt of Mail a paſſage found, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tody ruſhed, ſo that down he fell, and with a groan expired; the other three ſeeing their Companion thus ſerved, charged all three with deſperate fury upon <hi>Guy's</hi> high-proofed Arms, vowing Rebenge, the which <hi>Guy</hi> not enduring long, drew out his Maſſy blade which like a Commer portendeth death and diſmal fate, and after having brandiſhen it began to hew upon his Combatants ſo dreadfully, that at every blow their Armour (piecemeal) fell unto the ground, and afterwards their mingled limbs, ſo that two of them immediately fell dead, and the other wounded, on his knees begged life, confeſſing the whole intreague, how they had been hired to accuſe the Lady, and that Philbertus the Dukes ſon was really guilty, and had hired them for <hi>1000</hi> Crowns to do what they had done, at which an univerſal ſhout aroſe each prayſing and applauding <hi>Guy,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing the Duke, calling him Tyrant, each enquiring who the ſtranger was that had wrought ſo great a beliverance to the diſtreſſed Lady, and with all imaginable joy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed their thanks; <hi>Guy</hi> being rid of his foes, went to the Lady and unbound her, and delivered her to her friends, who embraced his knees, and weeping for joy, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ten thouſand bleſſings on his head, offering him Gold, Pearls and Diamonds, but he refuſed them all, and only deſiring them to provide for the Ladies ſafety, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying her out of the Dukes power, leaſt he being exaſperated, upon his being informed
<pb facs="tcp:35920:11"/>what had paſſed, ſhould deviſe ſome other means to put her to death in his abſence; ſo taking his leave he departed to the Ship, and there related what had hapned to his friends who with no little joy gave attention to what he ſaid, yet after ſome conſult, it was not thought ſafe to ſtay in that Harbour any longer, but wrighing their Anchors they ſet ſail.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Philbertus the</hi> young Duke having notice what <hi>Guy</hi> had done, purſued him by Sea and of a dreadful Fight that hapned between them, wherein the Duke and his men were taken Priſoners.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHilbertus</hi> having notice what had paſſed, how one <hi>Guy</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: three of his Champions, and mortally wounded the fourth, and that his treachery
<pb facs="tcp:35920:12"/>was diſcovered, the Lady <hi>Dorinda</hi> freed and conveyed away he knew not where, it ſo inraged him that he quaked with ire, and vowed the bloodieſt vengeance upon <hi>Guy</hi> that tortures could inflict, nor delayed he, but without his Fathers knowledge, cauſed his ſervants and attendants in number ſixty, to Arm themſelves, and ſtrait wayes haſted to the Port where he had notice that <hi>Guy's</hi> Ship lay, but no ſooner arriving there, but he underſtood that they ſet Sail ſome three hours before his coming, the which made him yet more eager, as thinking <hi>Guy</hi> fled for fent of him, and that <hi>Dorinda</hi> was by him conveyed away, ſo that going aboard a ſtout Veſſel that lay in the Port aforeſaid, he commanded to weigh Anchor, and make all the ſail they could after the Engliſh ſhip, whom by a ſmall Boat they underſtood was ſailed to the Eaſtward; the Marriners obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and having a fore wind and a ſwift ſailor, in ſix hours ſpace they came in ſight of the ſhip wherein <hi>Guy</hi> was, which bearing but half her ſails rode ſoftly on; no ſooner the French ſhip came in ſight, but the Marriners advertiſed their Captain of it, who with a Proſpective took an Obſervation, and aſſured <hi>Guy</hi> that they were purſued, and that their foes were trebble in number, telling him that the beſt way for their ſecurity was to hoiſt up all the ſails, and if poſſible, to out-ſtrip them, the which if they could do till Evening, he feared not but by the help of night to get clear of them; why ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> how many ſhips have us in chaſe, truly ſaid the Captain I can diſcern but one, yet that one carries thrice the men on board her that we have; tis no matter ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> Captain be of god courage, I ſwear I would not for the Crown of <hi>France</hi> have it reported that <hi>Guy</hi> ever ſled, no rack about and let us meet them like couragious Engliſh Soldiers, my ſelf alone will bear the brunt of war, whilſt you if you pleaſe may ſtand and ſee fair play; this ſpeech ſo incouragrd the Seamen, that they cryed, let us engage them ſtrait, and the Captain, now half aſhamed was no leſs willing, ſo that they had no ſooner put themſelves into a poſture, but the ſhip in which the French Lord was, bore up ſide by ſide, and without any more a do grapled with the Engliſh, which made Guy ſmile whilſt like <hi>Mars</hi> he ſtood upon the Deck brandiſhing his dreadful ſword; the French en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to board the Veſſel, which <hi>Guy</hi> gave order to permit without much difficulty, to that they thinking themſelves vittorious, gave ſuch a ſhout as made the Drean ring; nay now quoth <hi>Guy</hi> you have awakned me, look-to it, for this rudeneſs, ſome, or moſt of you ſhall ſleep until the day of Doom; with that he began to lay about him with more then humane force, whilſt Arms and Heads and dead men covered all the place whereon he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought, for againſt his Sword no Armour could defend, but at ruch blow freſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eams of blood ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> down, <hi>Philbertus</hi> ſeeing ſuch hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k of his Souldiers made, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thoſe few that were left alide to retreat if poſſible to his ſhip, and immediately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ungrapple, which <hi>Guy</hi> (having cleared his Deck) perceiving, leap'd on Goard the French ſhip, and alone for half an hour maintained the ſight with ſuch ſury that many of them leaped into the Sea, for to avoid his ſword, the which <hi>Philbert</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:12"/>encouraged his men all he could, and as a man grown deſperate with beſpair, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on <hi>Guy's</hi> Helm with ſuch force as made it ſparkle fire, at which <hi>Guy</hi> no whit daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but retuend him ſuch a blow as made him fall for dead at his feet, which the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſeeing, cryed for quarter, and threw down their Arms; <hi>Guy</hi> who was alwaies merciful to the ſubmiſſive, bid ceaſe the battle, in which ſpace <hi>Philbert</hi> came to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and with a low ſubmiſſion begged his life, which <hi>Guy</hi> as freely granted; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having tranſported him and the reſt that were left alive into his own ſhip, he ſet fire to the other; and ſailing onwards of his intended courſe, coaſting the Compaſs till they touched on that part of <hi>Normandy</hi> that borders on the German Empire, where <hi>Guy,</hi> nothing daunted, Landed; the which no ſooner done but he hears that a great Tilt and Tournament was to be held for <hi>Blaunch</hi> the Emperours Daughter, a moſt beauteous and accompliſhed Lady, and whoſoever carried the day was to have the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in marriage, and with her, a brace of Grey hounds, a Faulcon, and a milk-white ſteed; upon this welcome News <hi>Guy</hi> diſcharged the Captain of the Veſſel, leaving with him the Priſoners, who put them to their Ranſome, and code to the place deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the noble ſtrife.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Where Honour bated, their his Arms to try</l>
                  <l>And pluck a Plume from full fledg'd Victory.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> worſted all the <hi>German</hi> Princes, and won fair <hi>Blanch</hi> the Emperous Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who he afterwards left and departed for <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>GUy</hi> having taken his leave of his old friend the Captain, rod to the place deſigned for the Stage of Fortune, and the winning of the beauteous Prise, to which, he was lead by the loud ſound of the Trumpets, clarions Flutes, and all manner of Warlike M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſick; where no ſooner arriving, but he beheld the Plain filled with Horſes and Chariots and Armed Knights, whoſe Coats of Arms &amp; ſtreamers of Gold play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:35920:13"/>with the winds, and their might Armour and glittering Spears, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of the Sun-beams, made the place ſeem all on flame; a glorious ſight for to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, for moſt of the Chriſtian Princes and Chavalours Knights were there aſſembled with their ſplendid Retinues, thinking the Prise well worth their ſtrife, each being ambitious of the honour to be called the Emperours Son, and over and above to gain the faireſt creature that they e'r beheld; <hi>Guy</hi> was no ſooner ſetled in his ſtation, but the Trumpets ſound the Charge, whereupon <hi>Prince Philanus</hi> a German by birth entered the Liſt on his proud ſteed, who champing his ſilver bit ſcarcely endured the Reins; againſt him Earl <hi>Spartianus</hi> came, and both touching their Launces as ſwift as Lightning met, and with ſuch force, that the ſplinters of their broken Launces flew around their heads, then drawing out their glittering ſwords they furiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, till by a blow the Earl received on his Helm, his eyes grew dazy, and his ſword dropped from his hand, himſelf down from his horſe fell on the ground, which <hi>Guy</hi> ſeeing, grew impatient of delay, and ſetting ſpurrs ſo his bounding ſteed he came up to the Prince, now proud of his late ſucceſs, and laying by their Spears, they charged upon each other with their ſwords, but ere they had exchanged many blows, <hi>Guy's</hi> truſty ſword fell with redoubled force (much like a Thunderbolt) upon the Germans head, and breaking his Helm, bruiſed him ſo, that down he fell intran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and thence was carryed off for dead upon his Shield; to revenge which diſgrace done to his friend, <hi>Otton</hi> the Great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> proudly entred, vowing that <hi>Guy</hi> ſhould periſh by his hand, and no leſs then his life ſhould be ſufficient to appeaſe his fury, at which <hi>Guy</hi> ſmiling, ſuſtain'd his firſt charge without much reſiſtance, but at the ſecond met him with ſuch a blow as cut quite through his Armour and his ſhirt of Mail, ſo that from the gaping wound the blood ſtreamed faſt: which the Duke eager of Revenge regarded not, till fainting he fell upon the ground; and had not his blood been ſtayed he there had bled his laſt: Duke <hi>Rainer</hi> next came forth and bid defiance unto <hi>Guy,</hi> ſaying, preſumtious Knight this Lady muſt be mine, nor ſhall that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour guard thy breſt from death, ſince Armed with Love and powerful ſteel I fight, he had no ſooner ſaid, but <hi>Guy</hi> undaunted met him ſtroak for ſtroak, ſo that blows like hail fell thick and thundred on their Armour, till at laſt <hi>Guy's</hi> better blade wounded the Duke in his right ſhoulder, ſo that he could no more reſiſt, but down his ſole wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon dropped; this prodigious vallour ſo amazed the ſpectators, that long they ſtood ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, not knowing what to think, while various diſcourſes rumoured round, and the ignorant ſort affirmed it was no man that fought, but ſome-ſpirit transform'd into a humane ſhape; the Combatants ſtood mute, not knowing what was beſt to do, till the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> burning with Emulation, pricked forward his proud ſteed, and coming towards <hi>Guy,</hi> ſaid Sir Knight, to me unknown, whom Fortune has hitherto been pleaſed to favour, think not to bear theſe Trophies of honour hence, for they of
<pb facs="tcp:35920:14"/>right belong to me, ſo ſaying, he couched his Launce, but <hi>Guy</hi> met it with his ſword and at one blow cut it in ſunder like a Reed, then charged upon the Duke, who ſtrait began to ſtagger beneath the waight of his fierce Arms, making but weak reſiſtance, ſo that at a fifth blow <hi>Guy</hi> broak his Helm and bruiſed him ſore, at which he cryed for quarter, ſaying, hold dread Champion, for I yield; nor is there mortal power that can reſiſt thy force, I will no more with thee contend for woman-kind, whoſe ſtrength is ſo much more then man; I yield and do confeſs thou art my Conquerour: this ſaid, his ſervants bore him thence. After this Havock made among the French and Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Peers, none durſt approach the Liſt nor talk of Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ating with <hi>Guy,</hi> which the Emperour pereerving, ſent a <hi>Knight</hi> for him, with whom <hi>Guy</hi> went, and humbly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the Emperour and the fair Printeſs who ſate under a Canopy of State on his right hand; to <hi>Guy</hi> the Emperour thus began.</p>
               <p>Renowned Knight, tell me what place was firſt made happy with the birth, for ſure that Countrey muſt he proud of ſuch a worthy man, to whom <hi>Guy</hi> made anſwer, May it pleaſe your Imperial Majeſty, your faithful ſervant firſt in <hi>England</hi> drew his breath, <hi>England</hi> my Native Soyl, from whence I long have been detained in toiles of War; ſurely ſaid the Emperour that place muſt he impregnable that has ſuch a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work as thou for to defend it; great <hi>Alcides</hi> thou haſt ſure undone, &amp; <hi>Hector's</hi> Arms could not with thine compare: thou ever haſt deſeeved my praiſe redoubted Knight, nor canthe breath of Majeſty enough proclaim thy worth; take there the Virgin thou haſt won, accept her though ſhe is unworthy of ſo brave a man, and with her ask (except my Diadem) ought in my Empire, and ſle freely grant; to whom <hi>Guy</hi> bowing low returned all humble thanks, and excuſed the praiſes that he breathed upon him, at which the Emperour gave <hi>Guy</hi> a Jewel and departed, leaving him and the beauteous Lody to diſcourſe of Love alone; when <hi>Guy</hi> after due reverence done, addreſſed himſelf in this manner: Fair Angel, in whom Natures chief Perfections ſhine, on whom not without beſert the has beſtowed her choiceſt ſavours, moſt worthy to be abored and admired, command your ſervant to try his obedience, in whatſoever your Princely thoughts think fit, to which with a modeſt yet Majeſtick Grace the Princeſs thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
               <p>Renowned Sir, theſe praiſes are not mine, tis I muſt ſerve you now, ſeeing your Sword hath won me, ſince ſuch is my Fathers pleaſure, therefore forbear theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſies, leaſt your words ſhould make me bluſh and ſo betray the weakneſs of our loving Sex.</p>
               <p>At which <hi>Guy</hi> half o'rcome with Love, a while ſtood mute, and had been ſurely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by her prevailing eyes, had not his vows to <hi>Phaelice</hi> made, come freſh into his mine, whereat he reaſſumed his manly vertue, and drove aſſayling paſſions headlong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach, and after re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollecting, thus he anſwers: Fair Lady, in whom is lively ſtampt
<pb facs="tcp:35920:14"/>the Image of my Love, in thy fair face my <hi>Phaelice</hi> now appears, although my ſword has purthaſed thee with wounds, pet all I can do is but to be your ſervant, for know, my hearte'r I beheld your beauty, in <hi>England</hi> was linked too faſt for any ſeparation, except by the Tyrant Death that Enemy to Love: I have, ſaid he, a beauteous Lady, not unlike to you, to whom my vows are paſſed, never to be recalled, I had not thought that earth could have afforded ſuch another, but in beholding your perfections I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my miſtake, for her I roam the world about, to ſearch where <hi>Mars's</hi> Tents are ſpread, in bloody Battels and in Combats great and hazardous to venture all the ſlock of life that Nature lent me, ſo that if I through danger can eſcape, her promiſed Love is the fair Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el that muſt crown my toyl, at which he ended.</p>
               <p>And the Princeſs fetching a deep ſigh thus began, I ſee, ſaid ſhe, that Vallour dwells not in thy breſt alone, but thereby Vertue Reigns, which makes thy worth the more; ſure moſt happy muſt that Lady be to whom ſuch vows are made, and your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy appears ſo juſt and ſure, I ſhall not dare to break the ſacred by of Oathes, that link your diſtant ſouls; though I could with — at which the ſtopt, and turning ſighed, while bluſhes dyed her Roſy Cheeks, and all the Lillies were quite put to ſlight; then turning again, ſhe ſaid, moſt honourable man, here take theſe Jewels and preſant her with them from me, who muſt enjoy a bliſs I dare not think upon, Icaſt prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paſſion ſhould too great a Conqueſt gain over my frailty: ſo ſaving, ſhe after having received <hi>Guy's</hi> humble thanks departed, the place not longer being able to ſurpreſs her Love.</p>
               <p>Guy after leave taken of the Emperour, to whom he made his Love to <hi>Phaelice</hi> known, and the cauſe of his undertaken-travels and hardſhips, was by the Emperours command attompanſed to the Sea-ſide by all the Nobility of the Court, where imbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quing, he ſet Sail for <hi>England,</hi> as now hoping <hi>Phaelice</hi> would open her willing arm to receive the Hero that had bought her Love ſo dear.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Where Landing, he as ſwift as Eagles fly</l>
                  <l>Speed to behold the Center of his Joy.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> at his Arrival was Received by <hi>Phaelice</hi> and all the Nobility, how he is ſent forth again to ſeek new Adventures, but e'r he goes kills a monſtrons Enchanted Cow upon <hi>Dunſmore Heath,</hi> and is Knighted by the King, and many favours beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phaelice</hi> having received the News of Guy's Approch, and by the ſound of Fame heard all the Warlike Deeds his hands had done, and the Chevalerous Exploits
<pb facs="tcp:35920:15"/>(of which by this time <hi>England</hi> rung) ſhe prepares to receive him at ſo pleaſing a rate as might become his worth and Greatneſs, yet woman-like reſolving to ſtifle as much as poſſible her powerful paſſion, thereby to make him the more ſond &amp; cager in the chaſe of Beauty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> now arrived at <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle, where he heard the price of all his toyl in dreadful battel there remained, who at the inward gare carrended by her Damzels) ſtood ready to receive him, whom <hi>Guy</hi> no ſooner ſaw, but bowing low he thus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes.</p>
               <p>Fair <hi>Phaelice,</hi> from whom I have too long been abſent, how thy bright face re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhes now my ſoul, and feaſts my gazing Eyes, with beauty moſt tranſplendant, as when a long benighted travellour ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>counded with dark terrours, in a pathleſs maze, from the Orient sky beholds the comfortable dawn of Light, which uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers in the Sun's refulgent beams ſo? to inveſt the drowſy world with day; for Madam in the midſt of War, when Death was rageing round me, the thoughts of you inſpird me with double force, and gave me victory in all attempts, ſo that finding no more to do, I am with joy returned, to claim the promiſe that you made, leaving the Beautiess that this Sword in bloody Combates won, nor could the Emperours Daughter (though divinely fait, and next your ſelf, earths chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt Iem) entire my ſtay; her ſighs had not the pawer to make me falſe though through a Sea of Princly blood I waided to obtain her, yet when obtained, I left her, for your ſake, and only took theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ledges that you ſee for the recompence of hazards run; then ſay my goddeſs wilt thou now grant me a ſweet repoſe, in that loved boſome ſhall I reſt from bloody <hi>Mars's</hi> toyles, and cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t bright <hi>Venus</hi> in thy fairer Arms, ſpeak for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would gladly know.</p>
               <p>To whom <hi>Phaelice</hi> bluſhing replyed, moſt Honourable man, of thy great Exploits I am no waies ignorant, Fame came before and told them, e'r you came I heard what havock you have made, and what great Prizes you have won; but yet me thinks thoſe Beauties ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e been eſteemed more by you then to be left for ſuch trifles, But I know your anſwer will be, <hi>you did it for my ſake,</hi> tis ſure it was ſo, I believe as much, and will reward your conſtancy with Love, a Love as boundleſs as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ean, and chaſt as thoſe bright fires that ſhine by night: but to be plain I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold a ſecret Viſion that ſo me appeared, when I was cruel, and returned disdain for Love: In the midſt of ſlumber, <hi>Cupid</hi> from his Criſtal Manſion did deſcend, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to my view a Martial Here much reſembling your fell, commanding me to Love you for your great Renown and matchleſs Might, ſaying, the rerrour of the Nations ſhall he be famed to all Poſterity, Kings ſhall be proud to court him, and great Monarchs tremble at his frown, ſo ſaying he let fly from his bended Bow a glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Shaft, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xed in my Breſt, at which, awaking I ſound the kindled flame
<pb facs="tcp:35920:16"/>burn bright; but though I love thee dear, yet for my Honours ſake, muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Wed, till thy victorious brow be wreathed with more Lawrels, and when thou ſhalt return once more triumphant, then is <hi>Phaelice</hi> thine, and toilſome War ſhall teaſe.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid Guy. I muſt not yet discharge my servant Death, he muſt again with me, while from the terrour of this Arm each mortal ſlies, and Armies fall before me like Autumnal leaves when the rossing branches are aſſailed by gusty winds; come my bright goddeſs, as I ſtand within theſe walls of ſteel, incircle me in thy fair arms and cheer my ſoul with one ſofe Kiss, and e'r I do return, i'i ſend my Trophies home by Fame; thy longing ears ſhall hear of ſuch great Actions done, as ſhall make thee conclude thy ſervant worthy of thy Love. Be conſtant, faireſt creatures, and think upon the faithful <hi>Guy,</hi> who in the midſt of Arms and death will never fail to think on thee, that ſo at my return, Hymeneal joyes and the poſſeſſion of thy lovely bed ſhall crown my diſtant toyl in War; now look to it ye Champions of the world, Princes and Potentates, for <hi>Guy</hi> once more muſt wanter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'r the Globe to ſeek Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures out: ſo ſaying, he kiſſed her, and departed to take his leave of the moſt Noble Earl, whilſt ſhe with eyes brimful of tears withdrew to her Retirement, often ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culing her ſelf for puſhing him forwards on ſuch hazardous deſigns, and yet ambitious of his gaining Honour, and ſo between willing and unwilling, ſhe left him to his fortunate adventures.</p>
               <p>Whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> unto Earl <hi>Robands</hi> goes, who received him with more joy then can be well expreſſed, and orders a Feaſt to be made in honour of his new come Gueſt, inviting moſt of the Gentry thereabouts, who hearing of <hi>Guy's</hi> Arrival in <hi>England,</hi> and that he was to be preſant there, they came gladly, as being much deſirous to ſee him after ſo many great Exploits, the Entertainment was very ſumptuous, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with all manner of Muſick, and what elſe had power for to delight the ſences.</p>
               <p>Which ended, <hi>Guy</hi> following the Earl into his Retirement, told him that he came to take his leave of his Honour, and that he had made a vow to Heaven the which he burſt not violate, once more to try his Fortunes in Countries abroad, becauſe this my Native Land affords no great Exploits worthy to be Regiſtred by Fame: thus he ſaid, but would not make the Earl acquainted with his Love, nor that his Daughter had enjoyned the Enterprizes he deſigned to make, who endeavoured all he could to perſwade him to the contrary, laying before him the many hazards that muſt needs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and what dire miſhaps in ſuch daring attemps muſt needs befal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; at which <hi>Guy</hi> no waies daunted was the niore earneſt to depart, ſaying, he could not confine himſelf to Eaſe, but for the honour of his Country would ſpend ſome daies in War, and try the various moods of Fortune and of Fate, to learn for to contemn them both, and that
<pb facs="tcp:35920:16"/>his mind ſtill prompted him to great deſigns, the god of Battle at his Nativity being Lord of the Aſſendant.</p>
               <p>The Earl ſeeing his perſwaſions could no wares work on him to stay, diſmiſſed him, upon promiſe at his return he would abroad no more, but live at home with him; <hi>Guy's</hi> Father and Mother, bathed in Tears, likewiſe beſought his ſtay, but all in vain; for nothing but dread Arms and ſounds of War wire pleaſing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ears; all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in readineſs for his departure he embarqued for <hi>France</hi> again, to ſeek out new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentures, nothing fearing, though he knew that he had many there who would (it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) by strength or fraud, surprize his Life, but before the Maſter of the Veſſel could get clear of the Lands end, the wind turn'd about, and riſing ſomewhat ſtrong, forced them back into the Harbour, where they lay unknown to the people of the place who they were, then was <hi>Guy's</hi> Veſſel wind-bound ſix daies, in which ſpace Fame had noiſed through every corner of the Land, how that a dreadful and monſtrous Beaſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Majick skill into the likeneſs of a Cow, or rather a Cow of vast bulk poſſeſſed by ſome tempeſtuous ſpirit did terrify the neighbouring Plains deſtroying the Cattle round about, and putting all their Keepers unto flight, being ſo ſtrong and ſwift in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it was thought no humane force could have deſtroy'd it; the monſtrous deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her as followeth, is affirmed by Authors of great integrity and worth, that ſhe was four yards in height, ſix in length, and had a head proportionable, armed with two ſharp hornes growing direct, with Eyes all red and fiery, which ſcented to dart Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from afar, ſhe being of a Dun colour, from whence ſhe was named the <hi>Dun Cow</hi> and the place not many miles diſtant from <hi>Warwick,</hi> where ſhe haunted; from that Monſter took the name of <hi>Dunſmore Heath,</hi> which name it keeps unto this day, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Upon the notice the King had at <hi>York</hi> (where he then was) of the havock and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this beaſt had made, he offered Knighthood and ſeveral other Gifts of great worth to any that would venture his life in that encounter, but the terrour of her ſierceneſs had spread ſt ſelf in ſuch a dreadful ſhape, that none durſt undertake the enterprize, but each one wiſhing ſor <hi>Guy</hi> whom all ſuppoſed by this time in <hi>France;</hi> glad of this opportunity, he leaves the ſhip, and having changed his Armour to avoid being known, he takes a ſtrong battle Ax his Bow and Quiver with him, and ſo incognito riding to the place where this Monſter uſed to lodge, which was among a great thicket of trees that grew upon the Plain, near to a Poole or ſtanding water finding as he had paſſed along all the ſhepherds Cottages deſerted, and the Carcaſſes of men and beaſts ly scattered round about; he no ſooner came within bow ſhot of the place but the Monſter eſpyed him, and putting out her head through the thicket, with dreadful eyes glared on him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to roar horribly, at which <hi>Guy</hi> who was one of the expecteſt Archers <hi>England</hi> then had, bent his Bow of Steel, and drawing and Arrow to the head let fly, the which as ſwift as Lightning, striking on the Monſtr's hide rebounded as from a wall of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:17"/>not making the leaſt impreſſion, at which, whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> was wondring, out ſhe rame with ſuch ſpeed as ſeemed rather through the air then on the earth, and at him aimed directly her ſharp pointed horns, which he obſerving, lifted his Ax on high and ſmore her on the front with ſuch a blow as made her to recoyl; at which ſhe more enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged came on again, and clapping her horus unto his breaſt, dinted his high proofed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour e'r he could avoid her, but wheeling his warlike hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e unto the right he met her again, and with a redoubled ſtroke gave her a wound under the ear which was the only place ſhe was ſenſible of being wounded in, whereat ſhe roared aloud, and ſtamped the ground, <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving ſhe was mortal, followed that ſtroke with another no leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, at which ſhe fell to the ground, and <hi>Guy</hi> alighting hewed upon her ſo long that through her impenitrable skin he battered her skull, till with a horrid groan ſhe there expired, where, leaving her ſweltred in a ſtream of blood, he rode to the next inhabited Village, where he made known the Monſters death, to the unſpeakable joy of all that heard it, the poor people honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng him with preſants and thanks more then can here be told, thouſands from all parts flocking to behold that Monſter dead, whom alive they ſo much feared: long it was not e'r the King had notice of it, who ſent for <hi>Guy to York,</hi> where he no ſooner arrived, but the King embraced him in his arms, and after a ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did entertainment he gave him the order of Knighthood, with many other rich gifts, tauſing one of the Ribs of the ſaid Monſter to be hanged up in <hi>Warwick Caſtle,</hi> of which more hereafter, for now we muſt leave <hi>England</hi> and follow <hi>Guy</hi> into <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Where he ſuch deeds in Arms did foon atchieve</l>
                  <l>That they may ſtagger moſt for to beleive.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy Herauld,</hi> and two other Knights were ſet upon by ſixteen Villains that lay in wait for him in a Wood, whom he deſtroyed, they firſt having Kill'd two of his Knights afterwards aſſiſting the Duke of <hi>Lovain</hi> who was beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> he routed <hi>Lorain's</hi> Armies with great ſlaughter, and afterwards confirms a Peace between them.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>GUy</hi> haveing with much adoe got leave of the King to depart the Court, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly took ſhip again, without the knowledge of Earl <hi>Robands,</hi> or his beauteous
<pb facs="tcp:35920:18"/>Miſtriſs (who now doubtleſs would have been contented to have opened her willing Arms) ſo that with three Rnights more, (<hi>viz.</hi> Sr. <hi>Herauld,</hi> Sr. <hi>Edfrid,</hi> and Sr. <hi>Martis,</hi> who had entered into ſtricteſt Friendſhip with him, vowing to live and dye in adventuring for his ſake;) He landed after two dayes Sail in <hi>France,</hi> where in ſearch of Warlike buſineſs they croſſed the Country, <hi>but</hi> finding no enterprizes worthy of their ſwords, they bent cowards the Emperours Court, where <hi>Guy</hi> doubted not but to imploy his Arm, and gain the Fame he thirſted for, but the gerat Duke of <hi>Tuſcany, Orion</hi> by name, hearing of <hi>Guy's</hi> approach, ſuppoſed he came to deprive him of fair <hi>Blanch</hi> the Emperours daughter, into whoſe Favour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce <hi>Guy's</hi> departure) he had inſinuated himſelf, many wayes excuſing the foils he received by the Engliſh Knight, and therepon picking ſixteen of the beſt and ſtoureſt Souldiers he had in his Caſtle, he gave them Order to Arm themſelves and lye in Ambuſh in the Wood, near to the Road where <hi>Guy</hi> muſt paſs, be-before he could come to the Court; and as ſoon as they ſee him, to fall upon him, and after they had killed him; to bury him in the Wood, that ſo the Fact might not be known.</p>
               <p>To this command of their Lord they Redily conſent, not knowing what man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of man they had to deal with, ſo that placeing themſelves behind a thicket of Trees, they had not long waited before they ſaw <hi>Guy</hi> and the other three come rideing to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ards them, regardleſs of any ſuch Treathery; no ſooner was they within Reach, but the Ruſſians durſt from their Ambuſcade and charged upon the Engliſh Heroe's; Crying, Kill, kill, at which <hi>Guy</hi> and his three truſty Knights began to wonder what it meant, but long they wondered not, before they drew their Gliſtering ſtoords, Courage ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> my Friends, theſe Villains ſhall pay dear for this affront, with that he frowned with ſuch a look, as when the Skyer over caſt with black Clouds, portend dread Storms and Tempeſt through the devious Ait, and then let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y with ſuch force, and rage, as all that his Sword touched fell, ſlain or wounded, on the Earth, Armour all in pieces, cut Helms, and Helmed Heads lay ſcattered on the place, ſo dreadfully he layed about, that in ſhort ſpace ren of them lay breathleſs, but caſting round his Eyes, he ſaw the remaining ſix had ſo fiercely combated his three companions, that two of them were ſlain, and Sr. <hi>Herauld all</hi> beſmeered with blood, which flowed from Gapeing wounds at which <hi>Guy</hi> thus expreſſed his Ice; Villains whoſe lives fate has deſigned a ſacrifice to my revenge, let the Knight reſt and combate me, what do my Eyes behold two of my dear Friends (who left their Native Land for to accompany me) ſilenced by Death, and the third more dear then they, mortally wounded. This Villaines is the laſt vile Acts your hanvs ſhall ever do, with that he charged upon
<pb facs="tcp:35920:18"/>them with ſuch force as for exceeded <hi>Hercules</hi> when he the Centaures flew, and in ſhort ſpace cut five of them in pieces the ſixth upon his knees begged life, and did confeſs who had imployed them, and to what intent, whereupon <hi>Guy</hi> withheld his dreadful Arm, but it was too late, for the miſerable man only lived to tell the treathery, and dyed, thorough his Exceſſive Wounds; after which <hi>Guy</hi> not unmindful of his murthered and wounded Knights, went to a Hermits Cave not far diſtant thence, and gave him order for to bury the two ſlain, and to take in <hi>Herauld</hi> into his charge, and care, laying a grievous curſe upon him if he medled with the Reſt, and ſo departed (after leave taken) through the Sollitary Grove, bewailing much the Loſs of his dear Friends, yet not declining Honours ſearch, no ſonner had he paſſed the thick ſhades, but from a riſing hill he beheld a fair and Goodly City, before which on a plain were many armed Knights aſſembled to juſt at Tilt and Turna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nent, the which ſomewhat Revived his ſpirits, as well hoping to find Duke <hi>Orion</hi> there, and ſo revenge on him the Treachery, but he was not at that time ſo fortunate, for the Duke, by his Scouts, having notice of the death of his men, and that <hi>Guy</hi> was approaching, he feigned a ſuddain ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſo withdrew from Court; <hi>Guy</hi> being arrived, thruſt in among the thickeſt Ranks to ſeek the man he ſo much longed to combate with, but not finding him, he challenged all there preſant, and after having foiled the beſt that durſt encounter him, and wone the prize, he departed with great applauſe to the Duke of <hi>Millaines's</hi> Court: where no ſooner arrived, but the Duke embrated him in his Arms, and prepared a ſumptuous entertainment for him.</p>
               <p>Long he had not reſted there, before he underſtood that the Duke of <hi>Lovain</hi> to whom <hi>Guy</hi> had ſworn Friendſhip, was beſieged by <hi>Lorains</hi> power; whereupon <hi>Guy</hi> taking leave haſted to help his Friend, as he was rideing over a Moory Plain he met a Pilgrim, as he ſuppoſed, all Clad in Gray, who ſeemed faint with Travell, whom he kindly ſaluted and entreats for to acquaint him with ſome News—News ſaid the Pilgrim, and with that he fetched a ſigh, Alaſs ſir, 'tis a thing I now am no wayes converſant with, but have renounc'd the world and all its buſineſs, ſince I have loſt my deareſt Friend, and on his ſearth have travailed, and muſt travail with many weary ſteps, for till I ſind him, my ſoul can take no reſt, I pitty thee ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> but pray be ſo kind as to deelare the man, perhaps I may inform you for 'tis ſure that I ſhould know that voice, Alaſs ſaid he, it is a man renowned in arms through all the ſpaeious world, one for whoſe ſake I left my Native land and one who ſaved my lift from cruel Foes, with that <hi>Guy</hi> underſtood that it was <hi>Herauld</hi> nor could conceal himſelf, but pulling up his Vizage, diſcovered his ſate, and immediately allighting embraced him while he wept for joy, Expreſſing
<pb facs="tcp:35920:19"/>theſe words, and has kind Heaven been ſo propitious as to reſtore thy life whom I ſuppoſed dead: behold me <hi>Herauld</hi> I am he you ſought, henceforth let cares be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from this breſt, my only requeſt is now to know how your wounds were cured, to whom thus <hi>Herauld</hi> replyed with his Eyes o're flowed with tears of joy, Oh how can it be, am I thus unlooked for made ſo happy, then know worthy <hi>Guy,</hi> the Hermit with whom you left me in charge, after having conducted me faint as I was to his Cave, poured Balſoms into my wounds, and with ſoveraign Cordialls refreſhed my Fadeing Spirits.</p>
               <p>So that after ſome continuance in his Cave, I gathered ſtrength, but could not he contented in my mind, for loſs of you, which reſtleſsneſs the good old Hermit perceiving, was very inquiſitive to know the cauſe, which I as freely declared, upon which he delivered me this Gown to cover my Armour: that ſo I might the more ſeturely Travail in thy ſearch, the which has now happily been ſucceſsful, ſo ſpake <hi>Herauld,</hi> and <hi>Guy</hi> with joy again embraced him, and thanked him for his Love and Friendſhip, cauſing him to mount behind him, and ſo they Rode diſcourſing of their Various adventures, till they came to the beleaguered City, and breaking through the Hoſtill ranks of foes, came to the Gate where they ſoon found entrance, the Duke no ſooner hearing that <hi>Guy</hi> was come unto his Aid, but he came and humbly ſaluted him, bidding him ten thouſand welcomes, and each drooping ſouldier was revived at his Name; Crying, <hi>Lead on, Lead on,</hi> and let us ſally out and charge the Foe, the Duke laying hold on this opportunity thought it not convenient to let their courages coole, gave order to his Commanders to prepare for the Battell, and that on pain of death they ſhould be obedient unto whatſoever <hi>Guy</hi> ſhould think fit; this being done, the Gates were opened, and the Souldiers with ſuch a ſhout that Echoed through the Skies, Iſſued out, and charged the Foe with ſuch bravery and courage, that they with much ſlaughter, forced them to Retreat, broken and in great confuſion; <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> perſuing them even to their Camp, cutting their way through Armed Squadrons, and putting them to the rout, far and near, whilſt all the bluſhing plaines lay ſtrewed with dead and dying men, ſo that <hi>Guy</hi> in compaſſion unto Chriſtian lives, vid ſpare the ſword, and ſtayed the Souldiers fury, making ſlaughter ceaſe.</p>
               <p>This overthrow ſo vered the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> ſo ſore, that he immediately vowed revenge, giving order that all the Millitia of his Dukedome ſhould immediately march to retru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e his broken Army, ſo that within ten dayes he ſayed ſiege again, with Thirty thouſand Horſe and Foot, vowing not to leave the City till they had layed it as low as Earth, and thereupon begirt it with his Souldiers round, Reſolving ſo by curting off communication, to force it to a ſurrender, for want of
<pb facs="tcp:35920:19"/>proviſion, but the Stratagem prevailed not, for <hi>Guy</hi> and the Duke from the walls obſerving their intention, the better to diſencourage them in that point; like <hi>Manlius</hi> the Roman General, when beſieged by the <hi>Gailiſenes,</hi> in the Cappital, gave order to throw proviſion in abundance down, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſting the Enemy that if they wanted more, upon requeſt they might be furniſhed, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id <hi>Guy</hi> I would not ſtarve my for, leaſt when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown in bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhould excuſe his weakneſs for want of food; but now you have proviſion feaſt your elves that I may find you more reſolure in war then heretofore I have done, fore'r the ſun deſeends into the Weſtern Deean, dreadful ſlaughter again ſhall rage through all the bloody field: this ſaid he gave order to his Soldiers for to Arm while Drums and Trumpets rouſed their drouſy courages; then leading forth ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the moſt ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in three bands, the firſt Commanded by himſelf, the ſecond by the Duke, and the third by <hi>Herauld,</hi> the two firſt, each conſiſting of three thouſand foot and one thouſand horſe, and the laſt of two thouſand foot only.</p>
               <p>With theſe embattel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Forces <hi>Guy</hi> marching in the Van, charged the Germans in the Front, and with his word cut a paſſage for his ſquadrons through their pointed Ranks, that ſhivered Spears flew cound his head like hail; while this was doing, the Duke and <hi>Herauld</hi> charged on the right and the left of the Enemy with ſuch courage and bravery, that the Germans finding themſelves aſſaulted on all ſides, endeavoured to fly, and had left their Duke to ſhift for his ſafety amidſt his fors, had not pure ſhame reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Guy</hi> obſerving how they fell into diſorder and began to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ink together, preſſed them the more, and having made a wide gap with infinite ſlaughter of his foes, at laſt came where the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> fought, who no ſooner beheld all ſmeered with blood and what havock he had made, but by retreating amongſt his own Squadrons of horſe he thought ſit to avoid his ſury; and finding ſhortly after that the battle went againſt him, he cauſed a Retreat to be ſounded, ſo that in much confuſion he withdrew, leaving about ten thouſand of his men dead upon the place, whiles <hi>Guy</hi> and the <hi>Lovanians</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon the flying remains, tiſt they ſtiled the ditches and fields with the ſlain and wounded, even till <hi>Guy</hi> out of compaſſion ſtayed the ſouldiers from purſuing, and with the ſpoil of the Enemies Camp marthed hack in trumph to the town, where <hi>Guy</hi> was received under a Canopy, and a Trophy raiſed in memory of his matchleſs valour as their chief deliverer.</p>
               <p>After the Ceremonies were overpaſt, <hi>Guy</hi> taking the Duke into a private retirement, demanded of him, that if after this victory he would make a League of amity with <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> to which he joyfully replyed, he was content; why then ſaid, <hi>Guy,</hi> I ſhall he more proud to eſtabliſh a firm friendſhip between two ſuch potentates, than in innumerable victories, for I hold it not convenient for Chriſtians to war with Chriſtians, and muſt each other to glut the jaws of ſlaughter; but that we rather unite our for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es and dend
<pb facs="tcp:35920:20"/>our Arms againſt the raging Infidels who now tiranize over the Eaſtern world, late by Vſurpation taken from the Roman Empire: Sir, replyed the Duke, if you will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour me ſo far as to conclude this friendly League, what ever you ſhall propoſe I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly will ſign unto, <hi>Guy</hi> thanked the Duke, and with a thouſand Armed men marched towards the hill where the <hi>Loranians</hi> broken forces lay Encamped or rather ſcattered, and no ſooner coming to the foot of the ſaid Hill but he ſounded a Parley, at which the Duke ſent down his Lieutenant General to know the cauſe; to whom <hi>Guy</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade known his undertaking, and withal deſired a perſonal Treaty with the Duke, giving him to underſtand who he was; this being no ſooner known, but the Duke mounted, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by ſome of his choice Commanders, came riding down towards the Plain, the which <hi>Guy</hi> no ſooner perceiving, but giving order to his men to ſtand in battel ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, he ſet ſpurrs to his horſe and haſted to meet him, and in the midway they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lighting embraced each other, after which <hi>Guy</hi> thus began.</p>
               <p>Great Prince againſt whom (in our own defence) we fought, and heaven favouring the righteous cauſe, commanded Victory to attend us, which has adorned our Conquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Arms with ſpoiles, yet forgetting &amp; laying aſide all farther enmity or Quarrels, I from <hi>Lovains</hi> Great Duke, here bring you terms of Peace, for why ſhould Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans war, and Chriſtians Arms ſhed Chriſtians blood? then let it be no longer ſo, great Sir, embrace our offered friendſhip, and no more let us be foes; we impoſe no difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as Conquerors uſe, but deſire for to embrace with equal Arms: what though your Nephew was by accident ſlain, as the Duke himſelf confeſſes much againſt his will, which was the cauſe begat this war, your Highneſs muſt forget it; nay moreover when you conſider that thirty thouſand lives have made ſufficient Attonement to his ſilent Ghoſt, let us henceforth war againſt the Pagan powers, to drive them back to their diſtant <hi>Aſia,</hi> and rid <hi>Europe</hi> of ſuch a curb, ſo ſaid Heroick <hi>Guy,</hi> to whom the Duke replyed.</p>
               <p>Moſt honoured man, whoſe force in Arms no mortal can reſiſt, though I am much grieved for my Nephews death, by <hi>Segwins</hi> hand bereaved of life, and more for theſe ſhameful overthrows, yet at thy requeſt it ſhall be Peace, and hence forth horrid war in <hi>Janus</hi> Temple ſhall be locked up faſt, whilſt bound in chains on impious arms ſhe ſits complaining, with a hundred bloody mourhs: Go worthy Engliſh man, go tell my Brother, for now enmity is baniſhed, that's the name that a Royal Tent ſhall on this Plain be pitched, in which an everlaſting Peace ſhall be concluded for thy ſake, upon which, <hi>Guy</hi> thanked the Duke, and returning to the City, declared to <hi>Segwin</hi> what had paſſed, who embraced <hi>Guy</hi> and payed his labour with rich preſants and a thouſand thanks, and then iſſuing out in pompous attire, attended by all his Nobles, <hi>Guy</hi> being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in his Chariot on the right and <hi>Herauld</hi> on his left, they drove to the Tent or Pavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb facs="tcp:35920:20"/>of State where <hi>Sigbert</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> in ſplended Equipage attend their coming, where allighting they embraced each other with ſuch fervecy, as if enmity had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtranger to them, and ſumpruouſly feaſted each other for the ſpace of ſix dayes, ſo that the noiſe of war was turned into Ioy and delight, cauſed by all manner of noble paſtime, and at laſt friendſhip ſo far prevai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, that at the earneſt reaneſt of <hi>Guy,</hi> Duke <hi>Sigbert</hi> of <hi>Lorain</hi> gave <hi>Segwin</hi> Duke of <hi>Lovain</hi> his eldeſt daughter fair <hi>Miranda</hi> in Marriage, which doubly crowned the joy on all ſides, the which being ſomewhat abated, <hi>Guy</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of eaſe, requeſted forces of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oon Dukes to go againſt the Sarazens, who had then broke in upon the Greek Empire, and laid great part of it waſt, to which mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on they were very unwilling to condeſcend, deſiring him out of all love to ſtay with them, and not to hazard himſelf in ſuch dangerous enterprizes, but they finding him to perſist in his reſolution, and that they in vain perſwaded him to the contrary, entreated him to draw out what Forces he thought ſufficient, and that they would furniſh them with all things convenient for the war, at which Grant <hi>Guy</hi> returned them thanks, aſſuring them that he would ſo employ them to the honour of Chriſtendome, that after Ages ſhould wonder at their proweſs; and thereupon he ſelected two thouſand of the choiceſt ſoldiers preſant, one of <hi>Loranians</hi> and the other <hi>Lovanians,</hi> who were willinger to goe under his command then can be imagined, ſo he having Embarqued them upon ten ſhips of war took his leave of the two Dukes, with promiſe to viſit them at his return, and bring them ſuch Trophies as the fortunes of war ſhould deal him, whereupon they accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the ſhoar, and departed not thence till his ſhips were quite ſailed out of ſight.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So much he honoured was where e'r he came</l>
                  <l>And looked upon as the Eldeſt ſon of Fame.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> being furniſhed with two thouſand men and ten Ships of War, marched to the Relief of <hi>Bizantum,</hi> then beſieged by the Turks and Zarazens, and being ſcattered from the reſt of his Fleet, is ſet upon by 3 Pirates, two which he deſtroys, and forces the third to fly, Relieves the City, kills many of the Pagan Champions, and in his Return fights with a fiery Dragon and kills him.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>AFter a months ſailing <hi>Guy</hi> having coaſted <hi>Italy,</hi> and entered ſat into the Mediterranian Sea, where by a <hi>Levant</hi> Wind being ſeperated above two leagues
<pb facs="tcp:35920:21"/>from the reſt of his Fleet, he was ſet upon by three Turks men of War belonging to <hi>Sally,</hi> who ſuppoſing him a Prize, and that his ſhip was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>led with rich Marchandiſe, came boldly up and endeavoured to board him, which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving ſmiled disdainfully, and with many Heroick Expreſſions encouraging his men; he drew his flameing Sword, ſo drendfully known in War, and charged upon the aſſailing infidells with ſuch fury, that all he reached glutted the gapeing jaws of death, cutting their ſhrouds, Tarkell, and all other their Engins in pieces like a twine thread, whilſt <hi>Herauld</hi> and the reſt were not idle on the other ſide, for having prepared Pitch, Hems, Tarr, and Roſſin, they ſet it on fire, and with a certain Engin threw it into the Turks ſhip that engaged them, on that ſide (a Stratagem till then unknown) which catching hold on the Decks, Maſts, and Rigging, blazed into a horrid flame which ſeemed to curle amongſt the clauds, the which they being no wayes able to extinguiſh, with a dreadful cry forſook the burning ruined and leaped into the Ocean where many of them periſhed, which the other two ſhips ſeeing, hoiſted up all their ſails and endeavoured to fly, which one of them effected, but <hi>Guy</hi> having cloſe grapied with the other was leaped on board her, and there made ſuch ſlaughter that all the Decks were covered with the ſlain, which ſo amazed the Turks that they cryed aloud to <hi>Mahomet</hi> to come and ſave them from the devils that fought againſt them, but their prayers were in vain, till <hi>Guy</hi> out of compaſſion ſpared their lives, and putting forty of his men on board, ſent them with the remaining priſoners to his Friend the Duke as the firſt fruits of his Atchievements; no ſooner was this engagement ended, but all his ſhips came up with him, who by reaſon of a Fogg miſtook their way, ſo that Night coming on, <hi>Guy</hi> comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed them to ſtand off to the South-Eaſt, and ſail gently till Morning for fear of running foule upon the Rocks that are too frequent in thoſe parts, hid under Water, near to the ſhoares, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>No ſooner the enſuing morning had the Sun ſent forth his Orient Beams, but from his Deck <hi>Guy</hi> viewed the Coaſt, and from affar beheld a City beſieged, and heard the murmour of their ſhouts to vollue through the Air, much like the ſound of thunder almoſt ſpent, whereupon he ordered his Pilot to fathom for the next convenient landing place; which being found, he put in, and ſent Sr. <hi>Herauld</hi> with two more Captains to underſtand if poſſible who the beſieged and the beſſegers were, which meſſage they as willingly undertook, and after about five houres ſtay, return'd with this following account, which they learnt from a ſtragling Turk (whom they alſo brought with them as their Priſoner) that it was <hi>Bizantium</hi> made famous by the honours done to it by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and late the Metrapollitane City of the Greek Empire, and that the <hi>Sould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35920:22"/>with thirty thouſand men layed ſiege againſt it, his forces for the moſt part conſiſting of Turks and Sara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens, and that the ſiege had continued with much ſlaughter on both ſides for the ſpace of three months, the City being defended by a number of Chriſtians, under the command of <hi>Albertus</hi> a Noble <hi>Saxon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was not a little pleaſing to <hi>Guy</hi> who had now met with a fair opportunity of making his valour known, ſo that immediately he ſent <hi>Herauld</hi> and one Knight more to the Lord <hi>Albertus</hi> to acquaint him that he lay in the Port with two thouſand Chriſtians under his command, and that if he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d in the Evening open the Gates that looked to the Seaward, he would fight his way through the Foes and enter the City; <hi>Herauld</hi> and the other Knight undertake the Embaſſy, and in Turks habit having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the watchward of the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oner, they paſſed the Guards, and being come to the gate knocked aloud, and no ſooner declaring that their Meſſage was to <hi>Albertus</hi> but the Porter opening the Wicker gave them Entrance, when ſtrait they were conducted to the Caſtle where the General and his chief commanders were aſſembled in a Counſel of War, to whom after reverence done, they made known the cauſe of their coming; at the firſt mention of which <hi>Albertus</hi> and the reſt were ſomewhat doubtful ſeaſt it might be ſome treacherous deſign to win the Town, but when theſe Letter of credence under <hi>Guy's</hi> hand and Seale were produced, they ſtood no longer pauſing but recared them with all imaginable kindneſs; ſaying, that they would not only open the gate at the hour appointed, but likewiſe at the ſame time ſally out upon the Foe to make his entrance more eaſie and ſo diſmiſſed them with many expreſſions of joy: the time being come <hi>Guy</hi> landed his men as ſilently as poſſible, and drawing them up in Battalia upon the ſhore, gave order to thoſe that remained in the ſhips to ſtand off to Sea, till he ſignified to them his farther pleaſure by an appointed ſign, which accordingly being done, he marched towards the City, but e're he could gain entrance, the Enemy took the Allarum, ſo that Arm, arm, they cryed throughout, they came and drew up from every quarter, which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving held it no time to dally, but heartning his Souldiers, with teſting them the uprightneſs of their ſacred cauſe, he bid ſound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> charge, ordering his men to keep together in a Body, he draws his Sword which by Moon-light reflected like a Comet in the Air, the reſt ſoon imitated him, and giving a great ſhout the which was anſwered from the Town, they fell upon the Foes with ſuch undaunted fury that they bore down all before them, whilſt Leggs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cadg, broken Armes, and mangled ſhirts of Mail belleewed the Crimſon plain, <hi>Guy</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>forceing himſelf, with redoubled ſtrength the better to give his followers incouragement, had made ſuch ſlaughter where he fought, that the ſlain like ramparts hemmed him in, the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pure continued exceeding ſharp for the ſpace of two hours,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:22"/>ſo that what were ſlain by <hi>Guy</hi> and the fifteen hundred men he brought on ſhoat with him (the reſt being left to man the ſhips) and by three thou and who ar the ſame inſtant ſallyed from the Town, and charged them in the Rear, there periſhed of the Mahomitans no leſs then Forry thouſand, ſo that finding themſelves worſted on all ſides, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in much diſorder and confuſion retreated to their Camp, the which when the Souldian heard, he vowed revenge, and gave orders for aſſaul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting the City as ſoon as day appeared, it being then Night <hi>Guy</hi> ſuffered their retreat as not thinking it convenient to perſue them, he with his Souldiers entered the Town, and were moſt joyfully received, and the hurt men lookt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m with all diligence, <hi>Albertus</hi> embracing <hi>Guy,</hi> condu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed him to his own lodging, and there ſeaſted him as well as the place could afford, and ordered the ſame ſhould be done to all his Souidiers pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing away moſt part of the night in various diſcour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ning the aſſaies of the War, and what had happened ſince the firſt beginning of the ſiege.</p>
               <p>Next morning as ſoon as d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> light appeared, the Souldian commanded the Captain of his Army to prepare for the aſſault, ordering the Drums to bear and the Trumpers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound, at which the Pagans gave ſuch a ſhout as made the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ills reſound the Eccho back, which Rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed <hi>Guy</hi> from his ſlumber, who ſtarting up, inſtantly aſcended the Tower, and from thence beheld an innumerable Hoſt of Infidells marching towards the Walls with ſealeing Engins; whereupon he gave order to <hi>Herauld</hi> to get his men in readyneſs who cacefull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obeyed his command, then turning to <hi>Albertus,</hi> he ſaid, ſir, It behoves us this day for the honour of Chriſtendom to make a brave defence, in my opinion 'tis moſt ſit to meet thoſe dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>schers on yon plain, and there to give them battel e're they can reach our Walls, ſo that may be a means to check their pride, Victory has ſtood for us you ſee already, which will much animate our Souldiers on, and diſencourage our Foes, and ſer me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell you ſhe never turn'd againſt me yet, nor ſailed to pearch upon my Arms and ſavour me in all my hold attempts, follow <hi>Guy</hi> and fear not but <hi>Guy's</hi> fortunes will attend you; ſo ſaid the Warlike Hero of whoſe high courage <hi>Albertus</hi> much appraved cendering thanks to Heaven for ſending ſuch a Champion to defend the Town, long, they par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed not, becauſe the Enemy was at hand, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inging open the Gate, ſallyed our with twelve thouſand men at Arms to mae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them according as <hi>Guy</hi> had propſed, he with his Germans marching in the From, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is great Standard being a Lyon Rampant; no ſooner the Enemy beheld them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> march towards them who nor in the leaſt expected any ſuch thing, but they made a hair, and throwing down their ſealeing Engins put themſelves in Battalia, the which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving gave order to his Archers that were in the Front to
<pb facs="tcp:35920:23"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egin the Battell, who drawing their bows fent a ſhower of Arrows amongſt them, which galled the Turkiſh Horſe and forced them into diſorder, whereupon <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> broke into the main body, and killing or wounding all that oppoſed them began a dreadful ſight, ſo that the Germaines following cloſe after them, ſtill preſſed them to the right and the left with ſhort of Arrows, the which ſtruck no ſmall terrour to the infidells the Bizantines under the command of <hi>Albeitus</hi> imitating them in a ſhort time put the Enemies left wing to the Rout whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> fought in the main body, hewing his bloody way whiles death macked his Eyes, and whereſo e're they aimed he flew, nothing but rout and run incloſed him round whilſt Heaps of Slain lay like a Wall on either hand, fighting on untill he came unto the Squadron that was led by Colbron Lieutenant General of the Horſe, he being newly come to the Battel began to wonder when he ſaw what havock <hi>Guy</hi> had made, and how his Armes were all beſmeered with blood, and ſtaring with broad and ſiery eyes, he vowed reverge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wearing to ſacrifice <hi>Guy's</hi> life unto his Pagan Gods, this Monſter of a man being ten foot high and ſeven in circuit bearing a weighty ſpear, and ſuch a ſword as no man in the Pagan Army (himſelf excepted) could undertake to weild, ſo that preſſing forwards confronted <hi>Guy,</hi> crying aloud, Uile, Chriſtian moſt odious, to my ſight hold thy murthering hand and let us two each others weapon try, for e're we part I mean to ſacriſice thee to the Ghoſt of my dear Friends whom thou haſt ſlain, at which <hi>Guy</hi> fixing his Eyes upon him ſmiled, ſaying, thou art the only man I long have ſought, therefore let us loſe no time.</p>
               <p>With that they charged upon each other with ſuch fury, that from rarling Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the blows like thunder eccho'd, whilſt either ſide ſent ſhouts up to the Skies, <hi>Guy</hi> having born the brunt of the battel all that day, the Pagans doubted not but that their Champion would prevail, by reaſon of his monſtrous ſize and ſtrength, having been often tryed in dreadful Comba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, but they were miſtaken, for <hi>Guy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling his ſtrength, cut through his high proofed Armour, making ſuch wide wounds, that made him roar like the enraged Sea, when boundins from a hollow Rock, and endeavours to retire, but <hi>Guy</hi> purſuing him with one full ſtroak, cut through his Helm ſo deep into his head, that down he fell in deaths Convulſions on the crimſon Earth.</p>
               <p>At this the Pagans all amazed ſhrunk together, till <hi>Elmadant</hi> a fierce Sarazen charging formoſt encoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red <hi>Herauld,</hi> who ſought on the left, but long they had not engaged e'r he followed his Giantick Brother to the ſhades beneath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Morgadner</hi> another Collonel, monſtrous for ſize, deſperately engaged with <hi>Guy,</hi> having in his hand a battel Ax, which weighted about one hundred weight, with
<pb facs="tcp:35920:23"/>which he ſlew ſeveral of <hi>Guy's</hi> men before he could come on that ſide where <hi>Guy</hi> fought, but <hi>Guy</hi> no ſooner encountred him, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th his ſword <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut off his right arm, when falling down, and the loſs of blood he was traden to death among the croud, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unable to relieve himſelf: Thus the Battel going againſt them, the Pagans on all ſides fled, nor could the Souldian by his General poſſibly ſtay them being purſued by <hi>Guy</hi> and the <hi>Brizantines,</hi> the ſlain fell down by the way, to the number of twenty thouſand, ſuch havock made they of thoſe Inſidels, at which the Souldian ſtorming &amp; curſing his gods, gave order to recollect his broaken Troops, to hazard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce more the chance of War, and begin the battel, but all in vain, for the Soldiers dreading <hi>Guy</hi> far worſe than death were fled into the woods and Marſhy grounds without regard to their Coummanders, at which the Souldian was ſo much intaged, that whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> was tabing the ſpoil, he ſent a Chalenge to him demanding ſingle combate with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to: end the buſineſs of the War, which meſſage <hi>Guy</hi> moſt joyfully received; and all things being in redineſs, they met with ſuch fury as made the Earth to quake, the Souldian. being inraged by deſpair, and <hi>Guy</hi> couragious for the honour of Chriſtendome, laid o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him ſuch irreſiſtable blows, as made his gilded Armor fly like glaſs, and yield a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to mortals wound that followed thick, ſo that with one blow on the left ſide that entred his heart he fell down, breathing out his ſoul in curſes loud: this, <hi>Eskeldath</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloody and tyrannick Turkiſh Prince beholding, vowed revenge, and coming up to <hi>Guy</hi> defied him with disdaine, curſing him by all his gods, ſwearing he had vowed his head unto his Miſtreſs, and would hear it unto her on hi Launce; haſt thou ſo quoth <hi>Guy</hi> and drawing out his bloody ſword, ſaid, pray take it if thy courage will but let thee dare, leaſt the Lady think you did promiſe more then you are able to perform, and then perhaps you loſe her favour: this no ſooner ſpoak, but they charged upon each other, that fire ſprang out of their Helms like Lightning ſlaſhes, till the Pagan being wounded deep into the arm, let fall his ſword, and thinking it no time for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it up, he ſet ſpurs to his horſe and fled to the woods amain.</p>
               <p>After this Routand the plunder of the field taken, <hi>Guy</hi> returns victorious to the City, where he was received with all the pomp that can be poſſibly conceived, whilſt as he rode through the ſtreets, the people from the houſes tops, and windows, threw down Garlands before him, and ſtrewed him with ſlowers, crying, <hi>Long live the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Engliſh Champion, our happy deliverer,</hi> and aftewards ſet up his Starue in the Market place, adorned with the Enemies ſpoyl, the which was ſince deſtroyed by the Turks; <hi>Guy</hi> having ſtaid there with <hi>Albertus</hi> about ten days, was deſirous to depart and to return to <hi>England,</hi> ſo that leaving one thouſand of his men with <hi>Albertus</hi> for the guard of the City, he embarqued with the reſt, and ſailed back for <hi>Germany,</hi> but one day putting in to Harbour to refreſh; <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herau'd</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ar, and being
<pb facs="tcp:35920:24"/>much taken with the pleſantneſs of the Forreſt that bordered on the Sea, they entred the ſame to ſee if they could find any Veniſon, the which they had no ſooner done but a horrible noiſe or cry invades their Ears, at which, ſtanding ſtill to wonder what it meant, they heard it grow lowder, quoth <hi>Guy</hi> lets on and ſee what Monſters this wild plate affords; ſo paſſing along, at laſt they eſpyed a Dragon and a Lion encountring each other furiouſly, the which ſport pleaſed <hi>Guy</hi> ſo well that he ſate him down to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the fray, ſaying to <hi>Herauld</hi> whoſoever gets the Victory ſhall try the force of my keen blade, the which no ſooner ſaid but the Dragon had ſo overcome the Princely Lyon with his envenomed breath, that grown faint he turned aſide, at which <hi>Guy</hi> riſing charged upon the Dragon's ſcaly hide with force exceeding, fell yet as from an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine Rock, his blade rebounded, till at laſt eſpying a bare place under the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wing, he thruſt his ſword ſome too foot deep, ſo that with a dreadful yell the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon ſeemed to caſt forth a ſlake of fire, and with his guſhing blood his life expired; the Lion ſeeing his Enemy deſtroyed, proved not ungrateful to the deſtroyer, but licking of <hi>Guy's</hi> fect, and expreſſing all other rokens of kindneſs, he followed him to the Ship and then making as it were low obedience for the favour <hi>Guy</hi> had done him in killing his mortal foe he returned back to the Forreſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So to his Arms both men and beaſts did yeild,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Conqueſt crowns his brows in <hi>Mars's</hi> Field.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy,</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> travelling through a Forreſt, found Earl <hi>Terry</hi> wounded and his Lady taken from him by ſixteen Villains employed by Duke <hi>Otton,</hi> moſt of whom he kills and reſtores the Lady to her Husband, &amp;c.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>AFter a Months Sailing by ſeveral Iſlands, Caſtles, Cities and Towns, and the many various advent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites that hapned in that ſpace, <hi>Guy</hi> arrived in <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> where Landing, he and <hi>Herauld</hi> take their progreſs to the Emperours Court,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:25"/>which was then kept at <hi>Burdaux,</hi> where they no ſooner arrived, but the Emperour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice of it came to meet them, moſt Royaſly attended, where in the entrance of the Pallace he embraced <hi>Guy,</hi> with the endearing affections and favours that Majeſty could beſtow, honouring him with the title of Son; ſo much was our Heroick Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion oſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the greateſt Potentate of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endome, for his ſake the Emperour cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſumptuous Feaſts to be prepared, and Banquets furniſhed with all manner of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, and whatſoever could delight the caſt, whilſt the gazing crouds flocked cound the Pallace to behold him of whom they had heard ſo much Fame, each chanting forth his worthy Victories, and ſtriving to out-doe each other in ſinging of his praiſes, as the only worthy of the world: The Emperour cauſed Tilt and Tournament to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before him, but would not ſuffer <hi>Guy</hi> to enter the Liſt, becauſe he knew none would engage with him; after he had ſtayed there eight daies he deſired the Emperours leave ro depart that he might keep his promiſe with the Dukes of <hi>Lovain</hi> and <hi>Lorain,</hi> and with much difficulty obtain'd it, ſo loath was the Emperour and all the Princes and Nobſlity of his Court to loſe his company; but conſidring that the deareſt friends muſt part, they diſmiſſed him with great applauſe, who ordered the Captains of the Ships that then lay at Anchor in the Port to ſail homewards, whilſt he and <hi>Herauld</hi> troſſed the Country the neareſt way to the Duke of <hi>Lovains</hi> Court, the which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obeyed, whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> mounting rode on, but had not paſſed above ten miles, when entring a huge Forreſt, they on a ſuddain heard dreadful ſcreeks and a confuſed noiſe of <hi>Kill, Kill,</hi> toward which <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> directed by the ſound came inſtantly, where in a path they found a man wounded, lying weltring in his blood, whom they aſſighting knew to be Earl <hi>Terry,</hi> whereupon they raſing him up, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed how he came in ſuch a plight, to whom he (with a faint voice) replyed, that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving married with a beautiful Lady, <hi>Oſiled</hi> by name, whom before he was married unto, Duke <hi>Otton</hi> had requeſted in marriage, but ſhe by reaſon of his vicious life, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efuſed his proffer, in revenging which he had hired ſixteen villains, who having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice that he and his Lady was to walk that way, lay in ambuſh and had ſet upon and mounded him after that barbarous manner; and not only ſo but had taken from him his wife, whom more than life he did eſteem.</p>
               <p>And can the Duke ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> deal in nothing but treachery, I lately made his vſſiains repent in death ſo baſe a Treaſon, and if I can find out theſe that have thus wronged thee, they ſhall have equal ſhares dealt them; chear up my friend, and know that I am <hi>Guy,</hi> and by the Conqueſts that this ſword has won, and all the bloody Battels this hand has ſought, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fetch thee back thy Love if thou canſt but direct me which way the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ains went; at <hi>Guy's</hi> name <hi>Terry</hi> revived, and receiving freſh vigour ſaiſed his pale comtenance, pale for loſs of blood, and rendred praiſe to Heaven for fending ſo worthy
<pb facs="tcp:35920:25"/>a Hero to his aid, in ſuch a time of great diſtreſs, and then turning to <hi>Guy,</hi> ſaid wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſir, who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to pirty my misfortune, through that Lane they went by yonder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ak; this was no ſooner ſaid, but they heard the Lady ſereek, whereupon <hi>Guy</hi> ordered <hi>Herauld</hi> to ſtay with the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his wounds whilſt he pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch the Ruffins, the which he had not long done before he overtook them, halling fair <hi>Oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile</hi> after a rude manner: To whom <hi>Guy</hi> thus began.</p>
               <p>Villains, what dire miſchief is this that your vile hands have done, for which your lives are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eited to my revenge; reſtore the Lady, miſcreants and appeaſe my wrath ere ir heap deſtruction on your wicked heads; to which they ſcoffingly replyed, what would this vain-glorious fellow have, he thinks, tries another, to get a name by deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate folly, and that for being ſlain, in hopes of reſcuing this Lady, the world will pitry and lament his fate; a third declared that he was ſurely mad, which ſo enraged him, that bidding the Lady be of good chear, (for that he came to fetch her back unto her Lord) he drew his dreadful ſword well known in war, and with it laid about ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that ſcarce a ſtroke fell but he kill'd or mortally wounded one or other of them, bruiſing their Helms and Heads, breaking their Armour at ſuch a rate, that in an hours ſpace ten of them lay gaſping on the ground, which the trembling Lady obſerving, fell upon her knaes and entreated <hi>Guy</hi> to hold his Conquering hand, and ſhed no more blood for her ſake, at which <hi>Guy</hi> moved with pitty, put up his Sword, commanding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſir to ask the Lady forgiveneſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thank her for their lives, the which they durſt not refuſe, ſo that <hi>Guy</hi> giving them two or three luſty knocks a piece with his ſword in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eabard diſmiſſed them, bidding them tell their treacherous Lord that his name was <hi>Guy,</hi> and that he hoped ere long to meet him in Arms, and render him the reward of his trechery; after which <hi>Guy</hi> cauſed the Lady to mount behind him, ſo they cid to the place where they left the Earl, who ſeeing them riding towards him, faint as he was, came ſupported by <hi>Herauld,</hi> to meet them, where falling down he embraced <hi>Guy's</hi> knees, readring him a thouſand thanks, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nexpreſſible joy, ſaying, <hi>He ſhould be proud to dye fighting in his cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>So much renown in Arms the Hero won</l>
                  <l>That his great deeds through Europe now had run.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> went with the Earl to relieve his Father who was beſiged by Duke <hi>Otton</hi> and how <hi>Guy</hi> Raiſed the Seige, routed the Dukes Army and kill'd him in ſingle Combate.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>NOw night had caſt her Sable vail over the earth, and left only the imperfect brightneſs of the Moons ſilver beams to chear the drouſy Globe, when <hi>Guy, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld, Terry,</hi> and <hi>Oſlil</hi> his fair ſpouſe, had through the Forreſt, vaſt and wild, to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel
<pb facs="tcp:35920:26"/>many a mile before they came to any houſe or place of entertainment, but being ſo good company they paſſed on joyfully, till coming to a tuft of broad ſpreading trees, (that caſt a horrid ſhade, blacker then night it ſelf) they heard a hideous noiſe and roaring cauſed by Beaſts of Prey, who having left their Dens, followed the ſcent of blood, as Lions, Bears, Wolves, Tigers, Panthers, Leopards and the like, when caſting their eyes round they eſpied two Armed Knights ſtanding with their ſwords drawn on their Guards, and liſtning to the ſelf ſame eryes, who <hi>Guy</hi> and his aſſociates coming up to, found to be two Kinſmen of the Earls, at which <hi>Terry</hi> embracing them. asked the cauſe that brought them into ſuch a place ſo full of dread and danger, to whom they with a ſigh reply. Alaſs my Lord! to tell you news you would not gladly hear, your Princely Father in his Caſtle is beſeiged by raging <hi>Ottons</hi> Power, begirt with fifteen thouſand men, the incenſed Duke ſwearing to lay it level with the ground, and take your Fathers life in revenge of your taking away his Love.</p>
               <p>Alaſs ſaid <hi>Terry</hi> (with a countenance that witneſſed a thorow ſence of grief) I take his Love, juſt heaven knows my innocence, ſpeak Oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i, tell this Renowned man if I at any time procured thee to break thy Faith, or ever tempted thee to act ought againſt thy will; never, (ſaid the beauteous Lady) thou haſt been juſt in all, that cruel Duke has wronged thy innocence; indeed he did make known to me his horrid Love, but his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign (when I withſtood to yield) was to have Raviſhed me by force, but Heaven alwaies pittying the diſtreſſed, prevented his black intent; thine I am and ever will be till death ſhall make a ſeperation: Well ſpoke fair Lady, ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> in whoſe breſt are ſuch ſparks of Virtue, now I find that I muſt truly praiſe thy worth; tis for Love of a fair crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (far diſtant from this place) that I wars dreadful task firſt undertook, and through a Sea of blood have waded to obtain, and whom ere long I do intend to ſee, and lay my Trophies (gained by Conqueſt) at her feet, ſince I have found your conſtancy in perfect in their beings, fear not worthy Lovers ceaſe your cares.</p>
               <p>Alaſs my Lord, ſaid <hi>Terry,</hi> how can I be void of care and grief, when my dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (dear to me as life) muſt unavoidably be ruined for my ſake, if any guilt there could be in the caſe, ſurely I muſt be innocent, come then life or death, ile through the Leaguer break and free my Father, or elſe periſh in the brave attempt.</p>
               <p>Grieve no more, ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> nor let reſtleſs thoughts diſturb your peace; theſe Arms ſhall force the daring foe to leave the ſeige, or like to thundring with death h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>l ruine on their guilty heads, I in my Viſſage bear the cripple fates, and where ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e I look, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere deſtruction marks my frowns, and death a waights to execute my will: long have I wiſhed to meet the Duke in Arms, and now have found an opportunity unlooked for, and with as much joy go to this war as I would go to ſee my well pleaſed <hi>Phaelice</hi> ſmile.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:27"/>
               <p>At theſe words the Earl revived, and put on thearfulneſs whilſt he and his fair ſpouſe fell at <hi>Guy's</hi> feet, and would in humble thanks have kiſſed the ground, but that he taking them up in his arms would not permit ſuch reverence for to be done to him a mortal man, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So they marched on till they came within ſight of the Caſtle, the which ſtood upon a riſing hill; no ſooner had Fame conveyed the ſound through the Army that <hi>Guy</hi> was approching, but the Commander that had heard the dreadful exploits his warlike hand had done, fled and left the Duke and ſome of his perticular friends to order the Forces, the Duke ſeeing himſelf in this plight grew the more deſperate, vowing to continue the ſiege, though ten thouſand Devils were approching to give the beſieged aid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> after having diſperſed ſome few that lay againſt the Eaſtern Gate, with the Earl <hi>Herauld</hi> and the reſt entred the Caſtle, where finding the old Earl in much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, <hi>Guy</hi> comforted him, as likwiſe <hi>Terry, Herauld, Oſſil</hi> and the reſt, relating what adventures had befel, at which the old man ſomewhat revived, <hi>Guy</hi> deſired him to permit the Soldiers under his Command to ſally out upon the Fee, for ſaid he now fear has made half the Conqueſt, I in a minuts time will finiſh it, which ſaid, all with loud ſhouts cryed <hi>lead on, lead on, to Victory,</hi> when on a ſuddain the Gates on groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hinges opened wide, and out they marched againſt the Foe, <hi>Guy</hi> in the Front be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Battel with ſuch courage and fury, ſpurred on by keen Revenge, that the ſlaughtered rout fell down on either hand, and his men following it hard, in leſs then two hours ſpace the amazed Tuſcanes fled on all ſides in confuſion, leaving ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of their dead and dying friends upon the place, which the Duke ſeeing, in a rage deſperately minded, was reſolved to dye and not ſurvive his infamy, whereupon he ſought in every part for <hi>Guy,</hi> whirling his ſword about to make him room, to whom he approching, ſaid, now have I found thee who haſt haunted me from place to place, and challenge thee in Arms to try whom Fortune has deſigned to favour, for death is berter then an ignominious loſs of honour: to whom <hi>Guy</hi> thus replyed, proud Duke, whoſe treacheries are not to me unknown, who cauſeleſly ſent lately to envade my life, know that I joy to meet thee; at which they ruſhed together, and like Lions fierce en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred each other, whilſt from their Helms the ſparks of ſice flew, and ratling Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ecchoed in the Skies till the Duke, wounded deep on the right ſide fainted, and fell down for loſs of blood, the which <hi>Guy</hi> ſeeing, remembred that he was a Chriſtian, and thereupon began to compaſſionate his unhappy fate, ſtriving to recover him, but in vain; for ofter his having made a true confeſſion of his many crimes, and asked pardon of all whom in his life-time he had offended, the crim Tyrant death prevailed and led him captive to the ſhades of night; at which with a relenting mind, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving delivered him to his friends to be honourably interred, returned to the Caſtle,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:27"/>where with great joy he was received of all, eſpecially of <hi>Terry, Oſſil</hi> and the old Earl, but after having ſpent two daies there with much delight, <hi>Herauld</hi> and he took their leave and departed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Still ſearching glory's ſtage to court bright fame</l>
                  <l>And win themſelves an everlaſting name.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> killed a Monſtrous Bore, and of the Honour done him by the Dukes of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> and <hi>Lovain,</hi> how he return'd to England and killed a munſtrous Dragon in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and the honour done him by the King, and his Reception by fair <hi>Phaelice.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>GUy</hi> and <hi>Herauld</hi> having taken leave, proceeded onwards of their journey towards the Duke of <hi>Lovains</hi> Court, but not having paſſed far, e're in the Foreſt, they ſaw coming towards them the hugeſt Bore that Earth e'r bred, whoſe Eyes like
<pb facs="tcp:35920:28"/>two Beacons blazed, and on his back the horrid briſtles ſtood much like a Grove of ſpears; his Tusks which like two Ivory b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>works ſtood, were at leaſt two foot in length, his jaws with blood and ſlaughter all beſmeered, before whoſe rage, nor man, nor beaſt could ſtaud; but <hi>Guy</hi> nothing daunted, gave his horſe to <hi>Heraul</hi> for to hold and drawing out his maſſy blade went to meet him, at whom the beaſt coming with open mouth grunted horribly, <hi>Guy</hi> ſtood not to complement him but let ſly with all his force, as if <hi>lones</hi> thunderbolts from broken-clouds had feſt, ſo that the Bore never fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſuch weighty ſtrokes nor ſmarting wounds till then, turned tall, and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſave himſelf by flight, but all in vain, for <hi>Guy</hi> purſuing, laid ſo hard upon his ſwiniſh head that down he fell be ſmeered with blood, and with a horrid noiſe that made the Forreſt ſhake breathed out his life, after which <hi>Guy</hi> hewingoff his head, the which was at leaſt one hundred weight, bore it upon his Launce to the Duke of <hi>Lovains</hi> Court, where no ſooner arriving, but the Duke commanded all his Drums, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Clarions, and other inſtruments of War to welcome him, going with his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to congratulate his ſafe return, with all the imaginable expreſſions of joy, and ten thouſand happy wiſhes, ſending notice of his arrival to the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with all the Nobility of his Court, in very ſplendid Equipage came to embrace the worlds admired man, and to preſent him with gifts and honours, though not ſuitable to his deſerts, the two Dukes making a publique Feaſt for the ſpace of ten dayes for all commers whatſoever.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Guy</hi> having been ſo long abſent from the bright beauty who was to be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of all his dreadful toyl, was much deſirous to return for <hi>England</hi> his Native place, long it was before he could obtain their licences to depart, they ſtill preparing one noble exerciſe or other to delay him, till at laſt he opened to them his Love, giving them to underſtand it was for that that he ſo long had roamed about the world and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken enterprizes ſo perrillons, againſt which they could find no argument, but ordering one of the beſt Ships immediately to be rigged and fitted, they unwillingly diſmiſſed him after having accompanied him to the Sea ſide, ſaying, Go and proſper thou Renowned Worthy of the world, thrice happy is the land that gave thee birth, and more happy ſhe that muſt enjoy thee in her arms; may Victory a waight thee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe'r thou goeſt, and crown thy browes with new fading Bayes.</p>
               <p>For which <hi>Guy</hi> having returned his humible thanks, gave order to hoiſt up Sail, and having a good forewind, in four dayes touched on Engliſh ground.</p>
               <p>The which the King no ſooner hearing of but he ſent ſeveral of his Nobles to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his company at <hi>York,</hi> where then he kept his Court, <hi>Guy</hi> hearing that it was his Soveraigns pleaſure, ſtood not to diſpute, but joyfully accompanied them, though he had rather have gone to his ineſtimable jewel, the fair <hi>Phaelice.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:29"/>
               <p>Firſt no ſooner <hi>Herauld</hi> and he were conducted to the Kings preſence, where he ſate in his Throne with all his Nobles ſtanding cound about him, but they offered to kneell as was their duty, but the King forbade it, and riſing from his Chair of State, took them in his arms and embraced them, ſaying, worthy Champions, by whom my Realm is famous through the world, and eſpecially by you fir <hi>Guy,</hi> whoſe Arms have done ſuch wonders as amaze mankind, before whoſe arm the haughty foes ſtill bowed their ſtubborn necks; Monſters and Tyrants by thy proweſs fell, and Armies ſeat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſtrewed the field with ſlain, matchleſs in War, in Arms not to be equalled, Fames brazen Trumpet hath thy worth proclaimed, and thee the everliving Monument of true Heroick greatneſs ſtiled, ſpreading thy mighty Deeds unto the utmoſt cornees of the Laud, thou the Oppreſſors ſcourge, and the oppreſſed's ſhield, receive ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as a King can give.</p>
               <p>At which <hi>Guy</hi> bowing low, and returned all humble thanks, he thus begun, Dread Soveraign Lord, to whom I all Allegiance owe, your praiſes of my worth are too to great for my deſerts; but could there be an enterprize found out of greater difficulty, wherein your moſt obedient ſubject could do ought to merit the leaſt of theſe favours your Highneſs heaps upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, I ſhould think my ſelf for ever bleſt, a happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo infinite I ſhould be proud to purchaſe with my Life.</p>
               <p>Alaſs ſaid the King (and with that he ſighed) there is an enterprize of dangerous conſequence within the limits of this Iſle, but I muſt hide it from thee leaſt in ſuch a dangerous attempt I loſe the beſt of Subjects, and thou at home have thy Heroſek deeds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lipſed by foil or death.</p>
               <p>My ever honoured Lord ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> conceal not your Printely thoughts, give me that danger whatſoever it is, and i'l with open arms go joyfully to meet it were it the dreadfulleſt that ever Fate deviſed.</p>
               <p>Then ſince thou wilt know brave Engliſh Hero, tis a dreadful Dragon bred amongſt the Rocks in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> of a Monſtrous ſize, who for this moneth paſt has infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted all that Countrey killing both man and beaſt, ſo terrible to behold, that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple within ten miles of his Cave have left their habitations deſolate, and for haſt many their flasks and heards, the which he preys upon, and gluts his venomous jaws with ſlaughter; many of our Knights have gone to Combate him, but with ſuch fatal ſucceſs, that either wounded with his mortal ſting, or poyſoned with the infectious air he breaths, they have either dyed upon the plate, and there ſerved to gorgs his helliſh maw or ſoon after, and ſo cunning is the Feind, that if he ſees any number of Armed men regether, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will not deſcend from his Rocks, but there abide, or with expanded wings bear himſelf a loft in the air: I tell you not this becauſe I would have you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard your life in ſo perillous an enterprize, no I had rather that County ſhouldly waſt then you expoſed unto mortal danger.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:29"/>
               <p>To whom <hi>Guy</hi> thus replyed. Moſt redoubted Soveraign, the news you tell me has already filled me with more joy then can he well expreſſed, ſhall I that have freed ſo many Nations from the Peſts, now in the prime of all my ſtrength, decline the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, in which I firſt breathed my vital air, no, may it but pleaſe your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to order me a Conduct where to find this Monſter, or rather fiend, I now by all the favours that your Majeſty has heaped upon me, that before the Sun has twice rounded this Globe of Earth, his head upon a Launce, faſt fixed, ſhall to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty be brought, more monſtrous he cannot be then him whom I hereaved of Liſe in the <hi>Lovanian</hi> Forreſt.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Guy's</hi> earneſt requeſt, the King ordered twelve Knights to wait upon him, of whom <hi>Herauld</hi> was one, who had ſworn not to leave him in any adventure whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whereupon <hi>Guy</hi> te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k his leave, and the King beſtowed many bleſſings upon him, wiſhing him proſperous ſucceſs, and that he might be victorious over the deſtroying Dragon.</p>
               <p>No ſooner was <hi>Guy</hi> departed on his journey, but a Meſſenger from the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel then aſſembled at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> came to give his Majeſty to underſtand that his Preſence was required there, about deciding a buſineſs of much concernment, whereupon he poſted thither, where for a while we muſt leave him and follow <hi>Guy</hi> into <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where being arrived, he no ſooner came within keen of the Rock, wherein was the Dragons Cave, but he found the mangled carcaſſes of Men and Beaſts lye ſeatre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the Plain, ſome half devoured and others ſwollen with Poyſon; at which ſight not daunted in the leaſt, he forwards rides, bidding his Knights ſtay behind at ſome diſtance, leaſt the Monſter leaving him ſhould ſet on them, not ſo well able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his force.</p>
               <p>Having advanced within a furlong of the Cave, the Dragon eſpies him, and greedy of his prey, with broad wing out-ſpread, that drove the air around him like a Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind as he flew, came at <hi>Guy</hi> ſtaring on him with eyes that ſeemed to bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like Lamps of ſire, hiſſing horribly, <hi>Guy</hi> having ſet his Launce in his reſt met him with a full career, and hitting him juſt upon the breſt, his ſcaly harneſs burſt the Launce into an hundred peices without to much as making the leaſt impreſſion; at which he drew his ſword, and with redoubled force laid at the Monſters head, whiles he extended his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſling, diſgorging black poiſon on the ground, and with a dreadful Yell made at him with his teeth and claws, ſometimes on the Earth, ſometimes aloft in the air h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aſſails the Champion, who watching his opportunity as he was riſing, ſtruck him a full blow under the wing that ſpoiled his ſlight, the ſwarthy blood guſhing out a main, of which <hi>Guy</hi> taking the advantage, ran him in ſo deep, that reathing of life's ſeat
<pb facs="tcp:35920:30"/>with horrid yells that made the Rocks reſound; he breathed out his laſt, whilſt from his mouth that opened wide, was ſeen to iſſue forth a flake of five; his head with much labour he hewed off, and firing it upon the Truncheon of his Spear, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s hack to his Knights, who overjoy'd at his ſucceſs, welcom'd him and ſung him victorious Champion, moſt Renown'd on earth, placing a wreath of Laurel on his head, and ſo rid on till they came to <hi>York,</hi> but having notice of the King's departure they ſtayed not there but Poſted to <hi>Liacoln,</hi> where they were received with all the ſigns of joy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, the gazing c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouds from all parts came to ſee the mighty Champion ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſed by Fame.</p>
               <p>The King no ſooner heard of his coming, but riſing from the Counſel Board, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by all the Nobility preſant, he want to meet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, when beholding the Monſtrous head he bleſſed himſelf, ſaying, it was <hi>ſurely made to devour all mankind,</hi> ſuch gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Eves, and rows of Monſteous Teeth, Rabid jaws, armed with ſcale of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, and forked ſtings, whoſe points excerded the ſharpeſt ſteell, and at leaſt a yard in length, from which, ſaid he, her caſter Heaven defend this Iſle; with that he gave order to one of his Knights to receive it at <hi>Guy's</hi> hands, and afterwards embraced him with unfeigned joy, ſaying, weſt art thou worthy of our Royal favours, thou moſt Renowned of men, whoſe brave Erploits ſhine now as bright as the noon day-Sun, Honours firſt born thou art, and Eldeſt ſon of Fame, how ſhall we expreſs thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praiſes, whoſe all-Conquering arm no power of mortals can withſtand.</p>
               <p>The which <hi>Guy</hi> modeſtly endeavoured to excuſe, but in vain, for the more he excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the more he was honoured, the King ſending two Knights skilled in Limnick to take the juſt proportion of the Dragon's carkas, the which they did, and found it to be thirty foot in length, and alike in all proportion; the Picture being hung up in <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> Caſtle, but of that more hereafter: By this time Fame had conveyed to <hi>Phaelice</hi> the news of <hi>Guy's</hi> being with the King at <hi>Lincoln</hi> (the reſt ſhe having heard before) delayes not, but mounting her Palfry came attended with ſeveral Ladies thither, where finding <hi>Guy,</hi> who little expected her there, they embraced each other, and wept for joy; Alaſs ſaid <hi>Phaelice,</hi> my Love, couldſt thou neglect me thus, as to be in <hi>England</hi> ſo long without letting me know, tis ſure thou haſt forgot thy vows, or were they only feigned; to whom <hi>Guy</hi> anſwered mild: Bright center of my ſoul, on whom all my joyes depend, and all the dreadful toyles of War that I have undergone ſeem ſmall, ſince thou in recompence aford'ſt me Love; look on me my dear joy, my faithful heart is ever thine, it was ſtill with thee in all the dangers that I underwent, thou art the only ſhe this Land contains that willingly at my Arrival I would firſt have ſeen, but being fent for by the King, at my firſt ſetting foot on ſhoat, I was obleiged to obey my Soveraigns Commond, and after freed the land by ſlaying of the hugeſt Dragon that the earth e'r bred.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:30"/>
               <p>No more my Lord, ſaid <hi>Phaelice,</hi> I have heard of all thy brave Exploits, ſuch ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards you ſhall never undertake for me again, I am now thy own, in Loves ſoft wars we will hereafter contend; ſo ſaying ſhe wept for joy, and <hi>Guy</hi> embraced her, ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering her Tears with Kiſſes.</p>
               <p>The Marriage day propoſed, <hi>Guy</hi> gives the King to underſtand the ſumm of all, how for Love of beauteous <hi>Phaelice</hi> he had undertaken thoſe enterprizes, and waded through a Sea of blood, deſiring that his Majeſty would acquaint Earl <hi>Robands</hi> with the ſame, and procure his free conſent, for as yet he knew not of their Loves.</p>
               <p>This the King promiſed to perform, and that himſelf, his Queen, and all the Court would grace the Wedding with their preſance, the which was appointed to be kept at <hi>Warwick,</hi> the Queen ſending <hi>Phaelice</hi> many Iewels and other rich preſants, and all imaginable preparations great and coſtly were prepared for entertaining of the Royal Gueſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Whilſt Fame did loudly ſing his mighty praiſe</l>
                  <l>And Crown'd his head with never ſading Bayes.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy</hi> and <hi>Phaelice</hi> are joyned in Wedlock, and of their ſplendid entertainment, how afterwards be vows a Pilgrimage, and Travels to the Holy Land, how in his way he kills <hi>Amarant</hi> a monſtrous Giant, and delivers the Priſoners under his Tiranny kept in tortures.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>THe happy Nuptial day long looked for, being come, the King and Queen with all the Court to <hi>Warwick</hi> ſtrair repair, attended and adorned with all the Pompous Magnificence that can be imagined on ſo great an occaſion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:31"/>
               <p>Earl <hi>Roband</hi> no ſooner underſtanding by the King's Letter that <hi>Guy</hi> was arrived in <hi>England,</hi> and that for the Love of his beauteous daughter he had undertaken the dreadful toiles of War, and Combates fierce abroad, and eke at home, and that he was come to <hi>Warwick</hi> to ask his conſent, and being overjoyed he went to meet him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving him come towards him, bowed himſelf to the ground, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earl haſted, and taking him in his arms, embraced him with all the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Love and Friendſhip; <hi>Guy</hi> no ſooner asking his conſent, but his reply was, that he ſhould ever be bound to bleſs heaven for enclining to ſo Heroick and brave a man to ask that of him which he himſelf had ſo often wiſhed would come to paſs, and that his generation ſhould be ſo famouſed by an allyance with the worthieſt Champion that e'r trod the Globe; for which <hi>Guy</hi> returned humble thanks, and thereupon <hi>Phaelice</hi> being called, bluſhing with virgin modeſty, freely, and to her no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent yielded.</p>
               <p>Buſineſs being brought to this paſs, the Earl gave order for the ſumptuous Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment; commanding the Keepers of his Parks to prepare a hundred fat Bucks, which were ſerved up with all the choiceſt dainties of the Land, after the Churches Seal had joyned the lovely pair, Wine flowing round in ſuch abundance for to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Royal gueſt, that it was to be admired the Nation could affoard ſo much, all manner of Fowls and Fiſhes rateable, that the Air or Sea contained: ſo that <hi>Ahaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erus</hi> when he Feaſted all the Eaſtern Provinces could not outdo this; the Banque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ended, mellodious inſtruments of Muſick were brought, and the Ladies of Honour, and Lords, attendants on the Court, danced before the King and Queen, the Earl and his Counteſs, <hi>Guy</hi> and his fair Bride, who deck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with Iewels, ſate bright as the Morning Star, nor was <hi>Guy's</hi> one Father and Mother wanting to be there: after the Dances ended, ſeveral Playes were preſented and Songs ſung containing <hi>Guy's</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Acts, to the infinite ſatisfaction of all the Aſſembly, every one joying the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed pair, whilſt <hi>Hymen</hi> deſcending in a Cloud, ſung to ſoft Muſick, as followeth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:32"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>SONG.</head>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Happy for ever Bleſſed be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whom Heaven has joyn'd in Unity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let Peace and Honour ſtill attend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And joyes, ſuch joyes as know no end.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Still live in Love, and baniſh care</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whilſt I pronounce you happy are.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of War whom Beauty charms</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Embrace thy goddeſs in thy arm,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Live Live for ever in delight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loves ſoſter Wars does now invite</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To <hi>Mars</hi> no more dread homage pay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tis Love tis Love you muſt obey.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loves power commands, you muſt ſubmit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So has the Deity thought fit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt pointed Beauty, Armour's vain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Through it Love wounds with pleaſing Pain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then happy in each others bliſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Make Earth make Earth a Paradiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>After the Song ended, Maſquarades were performed, and all the noble ſports that could be imagined to delight the ſenſes; the Feſtival continuing for the ſpace of ten daies, but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long after, this joy was eclipſed by the death of the noble Earl, who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a violent Fever, to the unſpeakable grief of all men, making <hi>Guy</hi> ſole Heir of all his Lands and Lordſhips; the King confirming upon him the Title of Earl of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> he being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>henceforwards ranked in all aſſemblies of Councel and other meetings
<pb facs="tcp:35920:32"/>amongſt the Lords and Peers of the Nation, and highly eſteemed of all, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But to ſee in the midſt of joy and delight what ſuddain Eclipſes (at which the world not a little wondred) overſpread the bright ſun-ſhine of infant bliſs, for <hi>Guy</hi> tumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over the paſt actions of his life, began ſeriouſly to conſider with himſelf what an ocean of blood he had waded through to purchaſe his beauteous Bride; for which being ſmitten with remorſe of Conſcience, he fell into a deep Melancholy, and often retired in private to vewail his ſins committed againſt Heaven, ſaying, That to gain honour &amp; renown to pleaſe a woman, he had provoked the juſt incenſed God of all the Earth, and that his crimes were many, great and grievous; and that without ſpeedy Repentance they would prove his eternal ruine, with many other feeling expreſſions of deep ſorrow and contrition; ſo that his warlike eyes that were wont to ſparkle fire, now flowed with briny Tears, whilſt ſighs and groans declared the agony he ſtrove under.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Phaelice</hi> one day having watched him to his retirement, obſerving him in ſubmſſive wiſe, entreated to know the cauſe of ſo ſuddain alteration, ſaying, if ſhe had any waies offended, ſhe would upon her knees beg pardon, and be ſure for to tranſgreſs no more in the like nature; and with that ſhe tenderly wept, whoſe Tears <hi>Guy</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to behold, raiſed her in his arms and began to comfort her ſaying, weep not bright Angel, thou faireſt and divineſt of thy ſex, in whom alone ſuch vertues dwell as can equal the beſt of women dwelling on the earth.</p>
               <p>No my adoared Miſtreſs, tis for my boundleſs ſins that now turn back upon my Conſcience in their native uglineſs and vile deformity, whoſe numbers are as number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as ſands on the <hi>Barrachian</hi> ſhores, the flower of youth and ſtrength I have vainly ſpent, puffed up with ſond imaginations and the love of thee, in a red Sea of blood have I ſailed about the world, and with this hand laid thouſands ſilent, pale in deaths cold Tombs, who elſe might now have been alive; but thou art innocent of ſuch impieties, twas fortunate ſucceſs and my ambition that prompted me to ſuch extream ills, the which I now with Tears lament, and muſt to Heaven make ſatisfaction, for a long and weary Pilgrimage unto the Holy Land I have reſolved to take, my vows are paſt and ſhall not be recalled, therefore my lovely <hi>Phaelice</hi> weep no more, tis to the holy Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre i'l go, and ſee the place where my dear Saviour for ſinful mans redemption hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf ſo low as to abide in, after his having taken our nature upon him, and where he ſuffered and laid down his precious life for us unworthy miſerable wretches, who make it our chief ends to diſobey his will. So ſaying, he ſighed and groaned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, at which <hi>Phaelice</hi> again bedewed her beauteous face with Tears, the which he ſmothering with a Kiſs, and thus mildly did procaed; alaſs my fair one, for thy ſake I could willingly ſtay at home, but for the ſake of my immortal ſoul (more dear) I muſt perform my vows; live chaſt my <hi>Phaenix</hi> like the Turtle Dove, and win immortal
<pb facs="tcp:35920:33"/>praiſes by thy vertuous life: Remember the Renowned Women of former times, as <hi>Penellope, Edilfridia,</hi> and <hi>Edilthrudis,</hi> with many others, who after being marryed, accounted Chaſtity their greateſt pride, contemning all deſires of marriage bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p>I know thou art ſo much compoſed Divine, that thou canſt equal, if not excaed them all; for ſure it is twas for thy ſake, and to procure thy Love, that I trampled upon Crowns and Scepters, forcing Princes and Potentates to yeild their breaths, though I muſt confeſs the fault was only mine, and thou art innocent; but alaſs too long I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to make ſatisfaction: For my guilt Armour lye there, and all my Conqueſts he forgot, in a Pilgrims weed I now will Travel the world with weary ſteps: Come my dear and gentle <hi>Phaelice</hi> deliver me thy Ring, and take thou mine, the Pledge of our dear remembrance and Love, the which beholding, though diſtant many miles divided by rough Waves, let us think on each other; and if e'r I return to ſee this my Native Land, ile ſend it thee that thereby thou maiſt have knowledge of my arrival, he had no ſooner ended, but drowned in tears that burſt from her ſtarry Eyes, ſhe wrung her hands complaining againſt her cruel Fates, thus ſoon to ſeperate her from her Lord, begging on her knees his ſtay, but finding his reſolution fixed too deep to be removed, ſhe unwillingly conſented, promiſing to have him ever in remembrance, injoyning him the ſame by her, ſo unknown to any, ſhe accompanied him to the Ship in which he was to paſs for I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally, and there with a thouſand endearing Kiſſes took her leave of him, not knowing where ſhe ever ſhould behold him more, and ſo with ſad and heavy cheer ſhe return'd to <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle, where for a while we muſt leave her and follow <hi>Guy</hi> into <hi>Itally,</hi> where ſuffering many ſtorms at Sea, he arrived ſafe, and Landing only with a ſtaff and ſcrip travelled over the Countrey penſive and alone, paſſing many a wild Forreſt and Deſart place, till having gone about two hundred miles cloſe by a murmering Brook o'r ſpread with Poplars and Oſiers he eſpyed an aged Knight ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and greatly be wailing his misfortune, Crying alaſs! what now but woe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, which nought but Death can put a period too; cruel was the Tyrant thus to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave me of all my Sons, not leaving me ſo much as one for to ſupport and comfort me in my deelining age; Nay more, what horrour ſeizes me to think the miſeries they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, by his Tyrannick rage their deaths are lingring, but mine ſhall not be ſo.</p>
               <p>With that he drew his Sword and being about to fall thereon, <hi>Guy</hi> ſtepped to him and hindred the intended violence, ſaying. Reverend Sir, make known to me the cauſe of this your grief that has driven you upon ſuch deſpair, if it lye in the power of man to right your wrongs, perhaps I may be the man that will reverſe your woes.</p>
               <p>At which the Knight fixing his eyes on <hi>Guy,</hi> with a deep ſigh thus ſpake. Alas Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim, thou art not able to give caſe unto my grief, 'tis death alone muſt cure my plaint, be not ſo raſh ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> but tell the cauſe, you know not what hidden force theſe Arms
<pb facs="tcp:35920:33"/>contain why then ſaid he, kind ſtranger, ſince you will underſtand my miſery, know that yonder Caſtle large and ſtrong, dwells one <hi>Amarant</hi> a Gigantiek Tyrant, of ſuch a monſtrous ſize, as Earth I think never brought forth before, who feeding upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fleſh ſeizes all that paſs theſe Woods, and either dead or alive bears them to his horrid Priſon, in which not only of Gentlemen but tender Ladies he at this time holds Captive at leaſt one hundred, the Women for his Luſt and the men for his paſtime put to various tortures; my only daughter unadviſedly ſtraying this way, was taken by the Monſter, upon which my fifteen Sons, deſirous to reſcue her, went Armed to fight againſt the Tyrant, but not being able to withſtand his force were all taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, whoſe Lives I hear, for their ſiſters ſake he ſpares, but every day deviſes for them new torments: now thou haſt heard me out, what thinkſt thou? have I not cauſe enough for death?</p>
               <p>To whom <hi>Guy</hi> thus Replyed. Alaſs Sir, I pitty you, yet am glad I came ſo luck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily to ſave your Life, and free your Sons if yet alive; could you perform ſo meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a work ſaid the Knight, with humble thanks to you ide kiſs the ground and bleſs this happy day, but I fear tis altogether vain for to attempt, for many have whoſe Skuls lye ſcattered round the dreadful place: F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar not ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> lend me but your ſword and Armour, ile try that fortune which has never turned againſt me yet whilſt you ſtay here, and pray for my ſucceſs: So ſaying, he departed, and coming to the Caſtle Gate, thundred at it ſo loud as made the hollow walks to eccho, at which the dreadful Giant reuſed, came forth Armed from head to foot, bearing a weighty Club ſome ſix foot long, and ſeeing <hi>Guy,</hi> ſtared on him with Eyes that ſeemed to ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle like fire, ſaying, ſirrah, how durſt you thus preſume to hinder my repoſe? know you not tis death for to approach this place, much more to be ſo bold, it may be ſo ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> were your arms equal to your will; but it was to ſeek you that drew me to this place, know Tyrant tis not your monſtrous ſize I dread, to which the Gyant ſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, to an ill purpoſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thou come, for with thy fleſh will I feaſt the Fowls of the air, whilſt my ſelf ſhall quaff thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d, and with that laid at <hi>Guy</hi> with his Maſſy Club, who nimbly avoided the coming ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oaks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drew his ſword, ſo that a dreadful fight began, which long continued dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ful, till through exceſs of heat <hi>Amarant</hi> began to ſaint, which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving, redoubled his force and hewed upon his Armour till he dinted and cut it through in ſeveral places, which the crafty Giant finding, the better to recover breach, feighned thirſt, and beſought <hi>Guy</hi> to le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him drink of the adjacent Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and not to take the advantage of Natures enforcements, to which <hi>Guy</hi> readily condeſcended, ſaying, Drink thy fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, that ſo I may have the greater task to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or thee, who when ſubdued, ſhall have no excuſe, ſo ſaid Heroick <hi>Guy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Amarant ſtrait to the River haſted, drinking largely of the ſwelling flood,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:34"/>whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> ſtood prepared to receive him at his return. The Giant having ended his draught and quenched his thirſt, takes up his Club and comes at him with all his force, reſt having added freſh vigour; the which <hi>Guy</hi> obſerving, nimbly avoided the furious ſtroake, which falling on the ground entred above a foot therein, ſo that before he could recover his ſtroak, <hi>Guy</hi> ſtruck him full on the head, which made him recoil ſix huge paces, but wheeling about he charged again with greater force then before, ſo that the Combate having continued about the ſpace of four hours, <hi>Guy</hi> grew thirſty, deſiring the like leave that he before had graunted, to which <hi>Amarant</hi> ſcoffingly repl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he never was ſo great a fooll as to releive his foe, but to take all advantages; this ſo inraged <hi>Guy,</hi> that with force exceeding he ſmoat upon the Gyants Creſt, and with three blows brought him to the ground, who faſting like a Ciclops made the Earth to quake, and being down cryed out for quarter, but in vain; for <hi>Guy</hi> remembring his baſe ingratitude, immediatly lopped off his frightful head, which divided from the Monſterous trunk he fixed on the Gates, and taking the Key he entred the Caſtle, where he found the wofulleſt Spectacles that e'r his eyes beheld; tender Ladies in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k Dungeons, living for many years on humane fleſh, nay forced to eat their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, or their neareſt friends; ſuch was the rigour of the mercileſs Tyrant.</p>
               <p>Theſe he releaſed, but going farther, found a maſſy dore on brazen Pillars hung, he not having the Keys forced them open with Iron inſtruments he found in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where he had no ſooner entred, but he beheld ſuch ſights as made him ſtart with horrour, above fifty perſons (among which were the Knights Sonns) hanged up by the heel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, many of them with their heads downwards, other by the Wriſts, and ſome by the middle or Privy Members, all looking as pale as death, who no ſooner hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Gate open, but ſuppoſed it had been the Gyant coming to torment them (as his uſe was to make himſelf paſtime) whereupon they with lamentable cries began to beſeech him to put them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of their pains: But contray, <hi>Guy</hi> gently took them down, who through weakneſs were no wayes able to ſtand; when he had done this, he went and called the Knight, who no ſooner entred and ſaw what <hi>Guy</hi> had done, but falling at his feet he rendred him ten thouſand thanks, but <hi>Guy</hi> taking him up, embraced him, ſaying, he alwayes had vowed to right the wronged, and help the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed againſt the mighty oppreſſor; this he having ſayed, and they underſtanding he was their deliverer, with tears of joy bleſſed the day that gave him birth, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more this in which he had releaſed them from their torments; after which <hi>Guy</hi> having comforted them all he could, delivered the Keys of the Caſtle to the Knight, with ſtrict charge carefully to look to the diſtreſſed Ladies, and the reſt, he put off the Armour, and taking his gown and his ſtaff, departed towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with many a weary ſtep over Hills and Rockey Mountains, through Woods and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:34"/>where the dreadful wild Beaſts roared around him, ſoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itary all alone, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſitting down in the ſhade, or by ſome murmuring brook, would with tears bewail his ſins, and condemn himſelf for the many great tranſgreſſions he had committed, lamenting his youthful follyes, whilſt <hi>Wildings</hi> and Berries were his dayly food, and water from the Chriſtal Spring ſufficed for drink to quench his thirſt, whom now we muſt bewailing his depraveties, and return into <hi>England</hi> to take a view how <hi>Phaelice</hi> bears the abſence of her wandring Lord.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Whilſt through untroden muzes he does ſtray</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Juda's</hi> Land his ſins to purge away.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <head type="sub">How <hi>Guy's</hi> departure out of <hi>England</hi> is lamented, and of ſtrange Adventures that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel him in the Holy Land, how at his return he Routed <hi>Amantbuſes's</hi> his Army, and reſtored Earl <hi>Terry</hi> to his Lordſhips, afterwards returning into <hi>England</hi> which he found almoſt deſtroyed by the Danes.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>NO ſooner did the King and the Nobility hear that <hi>Guy</hi> was departed the Land on a Pilgrimage, but they were ſtruck mute with admiration, wondring that he could ſo ſoon leave the faireſt creature <hi>England</hi> had, for a toylſome and ſolitary
<pb facs="tcp:35920:35"/>life, yet commend his Piety that began ſuch early Repentance, and ſet his Soul at far greater value then all his Honours, or glittering Treaſures, ſo that for this he'l gain as much applauſe as before he had done for his victories.</p>
               <p>In the mean while <hi>Phaelice</hi> penſive, and ſhunned all converſe unleſs it were concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her Lord, keeping her ſelf reſerved and Chaſt, ſeldome being ſeen abroad, the Queen and ſeveral great Ladies came ſeveral times to viſit her, and to perſwade her out of her melancholy, but in vain; ſhe would not harken to tales of mirth, but often retiring ints her Cloſet, ſhe would bewail his abſence, ſaying, Ala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s where wanders now my <hi>Guy,</hi> what unknown Climate holds that far-famed man whom <hi>Europe</hi> lately held in Admiration; but now unknown in poor array he tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es the Deſarts thinking on me, whilſt Tears guſh from his brim-ful Eyes, and ſitting down under ſome ſpreading ſhade bemoans my loanly ſtate, wiſhing himſelf oft in my armes. Oh why did we ever part, for this ſhort moments bliſs that was ſcarce worth his thoughts, did he undertake ſuch toil and ſix years ſpend in dreadful War, alaſs! could it be my Lord that could leave me thus forlorn, bere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of joy, and comfortleſs, even in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dawn of Happineſs, overcaſting with thick Clouds of ſorrow the morning Sun, when all my hopes were growing perfect; a cruel Fate to me, but it is for the ſake of thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul which makes me bear it with the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s regret, and be more patient in thy abſence, hoping one day to behold thy much beloved face again, but where e'r thou art I know thy thoughts are fixed upon mae; thy heart is oft in <hi>England,</hi> though thou art far remote; tis ſure thou canſt not forget thy <hi>Phaelice</hi> whom once thou loved<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſo dear, no I know thou canſt not, I ſhould wrong thy Vertues ſhould I but imagine it; Oh my Lord couldſt thou but know how ſenſible I am of the great dangers that you muſt needs hazard your ſelf in, whilſt through Wilderneſſes large and wide you travel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>titute of food, and ly abnoctious, now unarmed, to the devouring jaws of each braſt of Prey, and your abſence bath tortured thus my poor bleeding heart with fear, which is worſe then death it ſelf, but whereſoever thou goeſt, this is my comfort my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends thee, though my body from the watery Globe's divided, Leagues without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>So ſaying, her eyes burſt out with Pearlly Tears, and ſobs ſtopped the paſſage of her voice, refuſing all pleaſant Wines or ſumptuous Diet, her delight being only to feaſt the Poor, and dayly to relieve with her own hand ſuch as ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e for Charity, whilſt her Lord having travelled through <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Paleſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> after many a weary ſtep ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the long wiſhed for place, the which to viſit in thoſe Popiſh times, was held<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſufficient to expiate all ſins committed till that time, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> took curious Obſervations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th of the Sepulchre wherein the Aramathenian depoſited the glorious body of our bleſſed Saviour inhumanely put to death by the cruel
<pb facs="tcp:35920:36"/>Iews, after that, the ruined Temple wherein he taught, as likewiſe Mount <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary</hi> or <hi>Golgatha,</hi> where his precious blood was ſhed for ſinful man; then the Reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Croſs, the Crown of Thorns and Scourge, and many other memorials kept in the Church, now built upon the Holy Sepulchre by the Patriarch. Having ſtayed there about ſome twenty years with great Devotion, he felt a natural decay, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Age ſtill hurryed death on; and being much deſirous to lay his bones in his Native Land, and to ſee his virtuous Wife before death cloaſed his eyes with long benighting ſlumber; he takes his leave to tread back again thoſe ſteps that he had trod before: Wandring through divers Countries and Regions barefooted all day, and when night came repoſed in ſome hollow Cave that Nature had Arched with Pumice, or beneath ſome ſpreading Oak, laying his head upon the Moſſy Bark; ſo paſſing on by degrees till he came into <hi>Itally,</hi> where long he had not travelled before he met with his old acquaintance Earl <hi>Terry,</hi> whoſe Father bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g dead, <hi>Duke <hi>Ottons</hi>
                  </hi> Son, by name <hi>Amanibus,</hi> had invaded his Tertitories, and having overthrown him in three huge battels, had taken from him his Lordſhips and Dominions in the revenging his Father, ſlain by <hi>Guy,</hi> and himſelf being forced to fly to ſave his life, which <hi>Guy</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, bid him be of good chear; for as I am an Engliſh man, ſaid he, I will do thee right, and bear the Vſurper back to his own <hi>Tuſcany</hi> at the naming of an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman, Terry</hi> revived, and with a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p fetched ſigh, ſaid. Worthy Sir, there was an Engliſhman once ſo much my friend as to ſave mine and my Fathers Life from the, aſſatling <hi>Tuſcanes;</hi> but I fear death has laid him low in ſome ſilent Grave, he not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been heard of in theſe parts for many years; his name was <hi>Guy</hi> a man renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned above the reſt of men: ſo ſaid, the woful Earl not knowing <hi>Guy</hi> (time having ſo altered his Warlik face) to whom <hi>Guy</hi> anſwered (not willing to make himſelf known) Moſt Noble Earl I knew the man you ſpeak of, and oft have ſeen him in dreadful Battels tryed, whilſt through the bloody fields I ranged and chaced the Foe with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſucceſs, ſpeaking in theſe ambiguous words, he deſired the Earl to fetch him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit of the higheſt proofed Armour and a ſtrong ſword, and then to Muſter up what men he had left, and leave the event to Heaven; in all this he was readily obeyed, ſo that in a dayes ſpace every thing was compleat for the March, <hi>Guy</hi> cauſing the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets to ſound aloud, at the noiſe of which ſome of the Tuſcanes aſcending the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Turcet of the Caſtle, ſaw four thouſand men (all the remains of twenty thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and the reſt being ſlain) marching toward them, of which they advertiſed <hi>Amanthus,</hi> who conjecturing it to be <hi>Terry,</hi> commanded his Souldiers to arm, and opening the gate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the town iſſue dout in good order about ſixteen thouſand ſtrong, marching in three Battalia's, which <hi>Terry</hi> obſerving would have ſled, but <hi>Guy</hi> hartned him on, ſaying himſelf would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egin the Battel and charge the whole Army through; long it was not
<pb facs="tcp:35920:36"/>before they came up cloſe to each other, the Tuſcans giving ſuch a ſhout as made the hills to Eccho; upon which <hi>Guy</hi> having drawn out one thouſand of his choſceſt men, ordered to ſound the Charge, and thereupon with force exceeding, engaged the firſt Embatteiled Squadron of the Enemies main Body, who dreamed of no ſuch fury, and bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e through their Ranks diſordering and putting them into great confuſion, whilſt <hi>Guy</hi> layd round about him, and at every ſtroke one or other ſlew: in the mean while <hi>Terry</hi> was not idle, for animated by <hi>Guy's</hi> example, he on the other ſide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Amanthus</hi> with the like ſucceſs, ſo that nothing but ſlaughter raged through the Plain, the conflict continuing dreadful for the ſpace of four hours, when the Tuſcans found themſelves infinitelp worſted began to ſhrink, and by diſranking fell into ſo great a diſorder that their Commanders could not draw them up, which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving, preſſed on cutting his way through Troops and Regiments, and making ſuch dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful havock that though <hi>Amanthus</hi> with many of his truſty Friends going through the Army entreated them to take courage, yet could he not reſtrain their flight, ſo that all retreat to the town, being cut off by two thouſand that wheeled to the right, they fled confuſed to the Woods and hills ſcattering themſelves on every hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guy</hi> and the Earl having purſued them till night, returned, where they found the Citizens come out to meet the Earl, with the Keys, expreſſing great joy, for thoſe that were left to guard it hearing of the overthrow durſt not attend the ſequel, but abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it and fled, which they no ſooner perceived, but they entred in great Triumph, and there that night the Earl entertained <hi>Guy</hi> with all imaginary ſplendor, even weeping for joy to be ſo unlooked for reſtored, deſiring to know his name that had wrought ſuch wonders in his behalf, but refuſed to make known who he was, nor did he as ſormer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, take any delight in Applauſes, or entertainment, but getting up betimes the next morning, left the City unknown to the Earl or any of his Attendants, ſo that journy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Sea ſide, he found a Ship juſt going for <hi>England,</hi> in which he joyfully Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued, the Veſſel being bound for <hi>Briſtol</hi> (which was then likewiſe a place famous for Marchandize) in eighteen dayes they arrived there, where Landing they heard moſt doleful and unwelcome News, for <hi>Canuce</hi> King of <hi>Denmark</hi> on a pretended quarrel for the loſs of his Father, who putting to Sea in a ſmall Boat, and a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt immediately arriſing he was driven on this ſhore, and being taken by one of the Barons of the Cinque Ports, was carryed before the King, who nobly entertained him, and for his great skill in Hawking made him his cheif Faulconer, which raiſed ſuch envy in him that he was diſpleaſed upon that account, that one day taking his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity in a Forreſt he ſlew him and fled into <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Murther being laid to the Kings charge, who was altogether ignorant of it, the <hi>Danes</hi> under their aforeſaid Captain, and ſeveral others under pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:37"/>but more out of greedineſs for Prey and Plunder, Landed with about twenty thouſand men, and after them ten thouſand more, with which they ravaged and laid waſte the Countrey, deſtroying with fire and ſword all before them, raviſhing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Virgins, and then ripping them up alive; daſhing babes againſt the ground, and all other horrid impieties that can be imagined; ſo terrible they dealt, that the people fled before them, dreading them worſe than a Peſtilence; the King having ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhered together the Engliſh Forces, had ſought ſeveral Battels in which he was worſted, and thereupon retired with his friends to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> a Town then ſo ſtrong that it was impoſſible to take it unleſs by ſtarving, Powder, that Helliſh En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, then lay deep hidden in the ſecrets of the Earth, and was not formed to belch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to mankind, againſt which the <hi>Danes</hi> having drawn all their Forces, beſieged it almoſt round, there being no paſſage in or out but at the Weſtern Gate, <hi>Guy</hi> upon this ſad News and diſtreſs of his King and Countrey thither he makes all ſpeed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to raiſe the Siege or loſe his life.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nor age detains him but through guarding Foes</l>
                  <l>He Fights his way and deals them ſtormes of blowes.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <head type="sub">How the King being Beſieged at <hi>Wincheſter, Guy</hi> undertook to fight with <hi>Colbron</hi> a Monſtrous Giant, Kills him and routs the Daniſh Army, forcing them with great ſlaughter to fly the Land, and then betakes himſelf to his ſolitary Cave where he lived many years unknown.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>GUy</hi> no ſooner entring the Town, but he went upon the Walls to veiw the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Forces how they lay Encamped, and what their numbers were, not in the
<pb facs="tcp:35920:38"/>leaſt making himſelf known to any: Long he had not been there, but out from a Tent placed on the Northſide, came proudly ſtrutting, an Armed Gyant of Monſtrous ſize, being at leaſt twelve foot in height and eight in thickneſs, he being the man that had ſo terrified the Engliſh and made great ſlaughter on them in all the Battels that were fought, none being able to reſiſt his ſtrength, but ſtill fled before him, he wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring underneath his high proofed Armour a ſhirt of Mail, and bearing a great two edged Sword: Long he had not ſtalked like a huge Coloſſus on the plain, but (diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfully) aloud he called unto the King, and thus began for to Revile, <hi>Athelitone</hi> now no more King of <hi>England,</hi> but our Priſoner, mued up within theſe Walls which we e'r long will Level with the ground, in vain it is to truſt to your defence, come forth and try your Manhoods in the field, dy here like men, and ſo perhaps you may purchaſe to your ſelves the names of Valiant; but if like Cowards there you ſtay, till we ſlaughter you within your walls, and roaſt you in the flaming Town, Infamy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poſterity will blot the falſe fam'd Engliſh Renown, which has ſpread wide into the world, a report of ſuch doowds as you never durſt adventure: Tis agreed by all the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of our Army, that if amongſt all your Nobles, you can find a man that dares to Combate me, in which Combate if he remains victorious, they will not only raiſe the Siege but depart the Land and leave you in Peace and quietneſs; ſo ſaid the proud inſulting Foe, at which their Armies ſhouted loud and gave him great applauſe. At which daring affront, the King being much perplexed turned to his Nobles, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if any of them would adventure on the Noble Enterprize: Remember ſaid he how great <hi>Goliah</hi> fell by <hi>David's</hi> hand; and ſhall this Pagan outbrave us thus, for ſhame my Lords let it not be known: Tis Heavens cauſe we fight, for the defence of the true Chriſtian Faith, as well as for our Countreys honour; who can tell but God may have put this offer into their hearts, either to free us from diſtreſs, or to deliver them into our hands: If none will undertake it, I my ſelf will Encounter with the haughty Foe, and if I periſh Heavens will be done. So ſaid the King, but all around ſtood mute, looking on each other who ſhould firſt Reply, which <hi>Guy</hi> (who had ſtood all that while undiſcovered) obſerving, with anger groaned, and coming to the King moſt humbly beſought his Majeſty to confer on him the Honour of the Combate, to which the King (not dreaming who it was, for all ſuppoſed <hi>Guy</hi> then dead, by reaſon he had not been heard of in ſo long a time) made anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>las poor Pilgrim, for ſo thou ſeemeſt to be, thou art not able to contend with one ſo Mighty, I had a Champion once, whom Death has now ſnatch'd from me, on whoſe head I would have ventured my Life and Crown, Oh — Renowned <hi>Guy</hi> for ever loſt, thou wouldſt not have ſeen thy Soveraingn thus affronted and abuſed, with that he turn'd and went, whoſe Royal T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars grieved <hi>Guy</hi> for to behold, ſtill with ſupplications, preſſing him that he
<pb facs="tcp:35920:38"/>would give conſent: Saying, Dread Lord, though I'm now unknown to you, yet truſt my Courage for this once, and by Heaven, I vow before the Sun deſcends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Weſtern deep, he that has braved you now ſhall pay his Life for the affront, at which Heroick ſpeech the King ſtood amazed, and wondred at the greatneſs of his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I have accepted thee, thou ſhalt be the man on whom I'l venture <hi>England,</hi> and immediately ordered his own Armour to be brought, which <hi>Guy</hi> retiring, put on, leaſt he ſhould be known, and girding on a maſſy ſword came to the King to take his leave, which the Nobles ſeeing, began to offer their ſervices, but the King would not permit them now, but embracing <hi>Guy</hi> unknown, ſaid, Go thou worthy man and Heaven di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thy hand to queſt thy Foe; at which <hi>Guy</hi> returning humble thanks departed, whilſt on the walls all ſtood for to behold the Frey: No ſooner was he come within call of <hi>Colbron's</hi> Camp, ſo was the Giant named, but he cryed aloud: Come forth preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Dane,</hi> who durſt ſo late put baſe affront upon Majeſty; behold me Engliſh born that am come to chaſtiſe thy inſolence, at which the <hi>Dane</hi> rouſing from his Couch whereon he was laid, came forth; where no ſooner beholding <hi>Guy,</hi> but frowning, and dreadfully glared on him with his fiery Eyes, and thus disdainfully began. And could the King amongſt his Lords find out no youthfuller for the Combate fit, but to ſend an old man ready to drop into the Grave, who weary of his Life growes deſperate, and fears not death, as knowing by courſe of Nature a few moments more would put a period to his dayes; tis ſure he ſent thee to mock me, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me more enraged; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be it how it will thou never ſhallt return alive; perhaps ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid <hi>Guy,</hi> if you can hinder it, but as wiſe and as ſtrong as you, have been miſtook; contemn not Age in me, theſe arms and my juſt cauſe ſhall ſoon decide the buſineſs of the War; ſo ſaying, they char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon each other with ſuch force as made their ratling Harneſs Eccho in the Skies, and fire like Lightning from each Helm flew; the Combate being dreadful to teh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, bloody and doubtful, the <hi>Dane</hi> never been ſo matched before, wounds were received on both ſides, whiles ſhouts that rent the Sky (from the Town and Daniſh Camp) were ſent, but Fortune who till now had ſtood neuter, began to turn on <hi>Guy's</hi> Victorious arm, whom ſhe had failed never, ſo that with a full blow, he cutting through <hi>Colbron's</hi> Armour gave him a wound in the left ſhoulder, from whence the blood flowing amain, he begain to faint and faulter, in his ſtrokes, which <hi>Guy</hi> perceiving laid the fiercer on, and redoubling his ſtrength, whilſt piecemeal down his harneſs dropped, whereupon the Giant entreated <hi>Guy</hi> for to deſiſt, and ſeemingly let him the Conqueſt gain, and he would promote him in the Daniſh Army: Fooll as thou art ſaid <hi>Guy,</hi> thy ſuit and Coward-fear are now to be deſpiſed, thinkeſt thou that <hi>England's</hi> Crown I'l loſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I loſe my Life; no know preſumptuous man how thou wert miſtaken at the firſt, and much more now at laſt; with that his dreadful blade he ſwings about his head,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:39"/>which in the air much like a Commet ſhowed, and with a redoubled blow, which like a Thunderbolt fell on <hi>Colbron's</hi> head, he broke his Helm and peirced ſo deep into his head, that ſtaggering ten paces back he dropped upon the ground, which the Danes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (contrary to agreement) came running to his aid, but all too late, for <hi>Guy</hi> had hewed his Head off from the Monſterous Trunk, and with his Sword drove the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered Squadron back, ſlaughtering them on every ſide, ſo that none durſt come within the reach of his Sword, but to the earth fell wounded or ſlain.</p>
               <p>The King from the walls perceiving in what danger he was in, with ſix thouſand all that he had left, Sallied out of the Town, and inſtantly came to his Reſcue, charging upon the formoſt with ſuch bravery, that he bore down all before him, who for loſs of their Champion were now grown fearful, ſo that breaking through their Ranks he diſordered them, and the Engliſh fighting courragiouſly for their Lives and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, made a great ſlaughter: whilſt this was doing, <hi>Guy</hi> who had retired to refreſh himſelf, being well mounted, returned to the Battel, cutting in pieces and deſtroying ſo terribly all that durſt oppoſe him, that all the place where he fought, lay piled with ſlain; ſo that having drawn out a thouſand Engliſh Horſe, he marching in the Front, Charged through the main Body of the Enemy, whilſt the King Charging their Left Wing put them to the Rout, ſo that numbers of their Cheif Commanders and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being killed and taken Priſoners they fled towards the Sea where their Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping lay, but the King and <hi>Guy</hi> reſolving to clear the Land of ſuch a Plague, purſued hard after them, not without infinite ſlaughter, for upon the News of the Overthrow, all the Countries through which they fled, with ſuch Weapons as they could get fell upon them, that of Thirty thouſand, ſcarce five thouſand got ſafe to <hi>Denmark,</hi> moſt of the Plunder they had gotten being likewiſe recovered, ſo great was the Victory that day.</p>
               <p>After the purſuit, the King and his Army returned to <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> where he would have made all the ſplendid proviſion for his unknown Champion that could be imagined, but <hi>Guy</hi> refuſed it, ſaying he had renounced all worldly Pomp, entreating his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to give him leave for to depart, the which the King would by no means conſent to, till he had declared his name, againſt which he urged many Excuſes, but ſeeing the King ſo deſirous, he taking him aſide, told him he was his faithful Subject <hi>Guy,</hi> and that after many and various adventures which hapned in his ſo long wandring up and down the Earth, he was come to <hi>England</hi> for his Grave, and ſo happily arrived as to rid his Country of its cruel Foe, entreating his Majeſty not to diſcover his Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val to any, not ſo much as to his Queen, the which the King promiſed to obſerve, and with tears embracing him, after a long conference gave him Licence to depart, only binding him with promiſe to ſend him word privately where he reſided, which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:35920:39"/>did, and the King without any Attendance came often to Viſit him in his ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Cave, where he lived many years.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So humble was the Warriour whoſe Renown,</l>
                  <l>And mighty Deeds, might juſtly claim a CROWN.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of <hi>Phaelice</hi> her behaviour for the abſence of her Lord, how ſhe came to have knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him, of his and her Deaths a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>als the deſcript on of their Tombs and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph, how <hi>Guy's</hi> Sword and the Trophies of his Conqueſts were hung up in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHaelice,</hi> not all this while having heard of her Lord, remains penſive and ſad, her only Recreation being to releive the Poor, who in numbers ſtill flock about her
<pb facs="tcp:35920:40"/>Gates for Alms, the which ſhe liberally diſtributed with her own hand, often enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Pilgrims that came from the Holy Land, if they had heard of one <hi>Guy</hi> her much loved Lord, and they anſwer no; ſhe would turn away and weep concluding he was dead, and then breaking out into paſſionate expreſſions, complain of her hard Fate, which <hi>Guy</hi> himſelf in diſguiſe often hearing, his eyes growing thereupon full he would turn aſide and weep to bear her company, many times receiving Alms at her hands, and reſolve not to diſcover himſelf: But at laſt finding Valours ſtrength decay, and that death approches faſt, he thought fit to ſend the Marriage Ring according to his promiſe, being much deſirous to behold her once more before he dyed; ſo that eſpying a Traveller coming towards his Cave, he called to him, and out of all love deſired him to do ſo great a favour as to carry a Ring to the Counteſs of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and if ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted of him to direct her to his Cave, he doubted not but ſhe would largely reward the utmoſt of his demands: The man at firſt ſeemed very unwilling, as not knowing what it ſhould mean, making many excuſes, till <hi>Guy</hi> preſſing more and more affirming that he meant no ill, but that the Counteſs would gladly receive his meſſage; he at laſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook it, and Poſting to <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle, knocked loudly at the gate, deſiring to ſpeak with the Counteſs in her proper perſon, for ſuch was his Commiſſion, no ſooner ſhe being come, but bowing low, he delivered her the Pledge of dear Remembrance, the which ſhe no ſooner ſaw but knew it and wept for joy; and ordering her ſervants to give the Meſſenger an Hundred Marks for the good tidings and went with him to the Cave where her Lord was, who eſpying her though feeble and weak, went out to meet her, where they embraced each other, not being able to ſpeak for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>md ſpace, till <hi>Guy</hi> thus expreſſed himſelf.</p>
               <p>Alas my Love, I ſee thou haſt well obeyed my will in every point, with joy ſince my return, I oft have heard thy praiſes told, how vertuous and chact thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd and above all, took pleaſure to releive the poor, my ſelf diſguiſed, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Alms from thy hands unknown. It was I that free'd <hi>England</hi> from the cruel Danes, and ever ſince have had my Lodging in this Cave, oft fed on Roots and drank Water from the Brook, ſhedding tears for true Repentance for my crying ſins, and now have made my peace with Heaven; he would have proceeded but ſhe interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, and fetching a deep ſigh cryed: Ah my dear Lord, and could you be ſo cruel to your mournful <hi>Phaelice</hi> thus long to conceal your ſelf from her that with ſuch earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enquired after you, but in vain, no news of you e'r reached my longing Ear: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las ſaid <hi>Guy</hi> it was for the welfare of my immortal Soul that I made not my ſelf nor ſolitary dwelling known, nor ſhould I now have done (though Heaven knows I love thee above all earthly things) had not this mortal ſickneſs ſeized me, and according to my promiſe I deſired to embrace thee once before I dye; weep not my Love, tis but a
<pb facs="tcp:35920:41"/>ſhort ſpace and we ſhall meet in Heaven never to be ſeperated more; this being no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſaid, but a fit of his Diſeaſe ſeized him he fell into a ſwound, whereupon ſhe with much rubbing and ſprinkling of water in his face, with the aſſiſtance of the Travellor, brought him to life again; then ſending for her ſervants, ordered them to fetch all manner of Cordials, and would have removed her Lord to his Caſtel, but he would in no wiſe conſent to it, ſaying, he had choſen that ſilent place quietly there to reſign his breath, the which he did accordingly in two daies after, commending his immortal ſoul into the hands of his great Creator, leaving her ſole Poſſeſſor of all his worldly Goods to diſpoſe of them as ſhe thought good, during which ſpace of Life ſhe would not leave him, but warched with him in the cold Cave, and no ſooner perceiving his immortal ſoul had taken ſlight, but ſhe cryed, Ah cruel death then wilt thou let me ſlay, no I will but follow my dear Lord to his Eternal place; which ſaid, ſhe in the height of Diſtraction beat her ſnowy breaſts, tore off her golden hair, and mangled her face, and had done greater violence had they not reſtrayn'd her; then embracing the dead Corps, ſhe fell into a ſwound, which her ſervants perceiving, conveyed her with the body of her departed Lord to <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle: Long it was not before the fame of <hi>Guy's</hi> death (that great Champion of the World, whoſe equal <hi>Europe</hi> could never boaſt of ſince or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) ſpread through the Land, whereupon the King and Queen left <hi>York</hi> and came to <hi>Warwick</hi> to give order for the Burial of ſo Renowned a Subject, and like wiſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort his of conſolate Lady; but could not effect the latter, for ſhe ſhun'd all converſe, delighting more in ſolitary Darkneſs than in Light, refuſing either meat or drink for three dayes ſpace; in the mean while <hi>Guy's</hi> Corps by the King's order was Imbalmed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d all the Caſtle hung with mourning to the ground, but while they were ſumpteouſly preparing for his Funeral, the Counteſs through extream grief fell into a violent Fever of which in deſpight of Art in a ſhort ſpace ſhe dyed, and breathing out her Soul, cryed, now my Lord with joy I come to enjoy thy company for ever in bright Manſions far above the Starry Skies.</p>
               <p>This renewed the former Grief throughout the Nation, each exclaiming againſt the Tyranny of Death, who had bereaved them in ſo ſhort a ſpace of the moſt Renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pair the Nation ever bred, the one for Matchleſs Deeds in Arms, the other for matchleſs Beauty and Vertue.</p>
               <p>The King gave order to Erect a ſpatious Monument over the Tomb deſigned for them, on which was Carved <hi>Guy's</hi> Noble and Heroick deeds with both their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, lying as it were a ſleep,, whilſt Angels ſtrewed Roſes and fragrant flowers around them, and placed Garlands on their heads: The time of the Solemnity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come; all the Nobility in <hi>England</hi> in Mourning attended the Beirs, the King &amp; Queen being chief mourners, whilſt the Trumpets ſounded dolefully before them,
<pb facs="tcp:35920:41"/>and the Prieſts their <hi>Requiems</hi> Sung, their bodies were laid hath Tombe, and this Cpitaph was infixed, &amp;c.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>EPITAPH.</p>
                  <l>Under this ſacred Pile of Marble Stone</l>
                  <l>Doe lye the <hi>Wonders</hi> of the World, whom none</l>
                  <l>Could ever match, her's <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Beauties</hi> Pride,</l>
                  <l>The far-Famed <hi>Bridegroome</hi> and his lovely <hi>Bride.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> here Entombed lye</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe <hi>Names</hi> Immortal are and cannot Dye.</l>
               </q>
               <p>After this, the King cauſed <hi>Guy's</hi> Sword with which he fought moſt of his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Battels withal, the Head of the Dragon killed in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Dun Cow, with ſeveral other Trophies of his Conqueſt, to be hanged up in <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle; as likewiſe on Cloth of Arras, the full proportion of the Monſtrous Dragon which was about thirty foot in length; appointing a man a yearly Sallary to keep them, ſome of which are remaining to this day, and may be ſeen for the better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the curious or incredulous of the Age, which will hardly be induced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ever ſuch Worthies were, though Scripture it ſelf makes mention of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>A Book of FORTUNE with Prophetical Solutions, Giving Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in every condition of humane Life, either as it relates to Love or buſineſs. Written in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and ever ſince carefully preſerved by a Monk beyond Sea, and now brought over into <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>George Stranmore</hi> Gent. Sold by <hi>Philip Brooksby</hi> at his Shop, the ſign of the <hi>Golden Ball,</hi> in <hi>weſt-ſmithfield</hi> near the <hi>Hoſpital Gate.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35920:42"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Faithful Collection of the Neweſt, and moſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Songs that are ſung at Court and both the Theatres.</p>
            <p>Honours Preſervation without blood, or a ſober advice to Duelliſts. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Compendious Tract of the moſt Exquiſite Nature to appeaſe the ſudden Fits of Fury, which Engliſh ſpirits have of late been too much ſubject too, with many cautions how without the loſs of Reputation, or the leaſt imprint of Cowardiſe, as well the Nobility as Gentry of this Nation may refuſe to Hazard their Lives and Fortunes on ſuch mean pretences of Vindicating a <hi>Miſcalled Honour</hi> or <hi>Unmanly Gallantry,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe what dangerous inconveniencies men thruſt themſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in ſuch caſes, with an account how ſuch Duels prove plain Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and are contrary to the Laws of God and Man.</p>
            <p>There newly Printed for and ſold by <hi>Philip Brooksby</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> near the <hi>Hoſpital Gate</hi> in <hi>Weſt-ſmithfield,</hi> where any Engliſh or Iriſh Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may be furniſhed with all ſorts of Hiſtories, ſmall books or Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads at reaſonable Rates.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35920:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
